<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<records xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://doaj.org/static/doaj/doajArticles.xsd">
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.1</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>25</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Prologue: Wind of change from the Ural Mountains to Atlantic Lusitania between the forth
            and the seventh centuries AD
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Francesca Carboni</name>
                <email>francesca.carboni@ugent.be</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Department of Archaeology, Ghent University</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/25</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords/>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.2</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>26</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Early medieval settlements and land use in the Kislovodsk basin (North Caucasus)</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>D.S. Korobov</name>
                <email>dkorobov@mail.ru</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Institute of Archaeology, Russian Academy of Sciences Dm. Uljanova str.,
                19, 117036, Moscow, Russia
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">In the context of searching for agricultural landscapes which have escaped recent
            anthropogenic disturbance, the evidence of the Kislovodsk basin (North Caucasus) has special importance. Its
            sheltered location and the fact that it is relatively well-studied, enable us to create, for the first time
            in Russia, an archaeological Geographic Information System (GIS) for the microregion, which currently
            includes data on over 920 archaeological sites, from the Aeneolithic to modern times. Preliminary analysis
            of the archaeological record of the Kislovodsk basin has revealed that the Early Medieval period dating to
            the fifth - eight centuries AD was characterised by the highest population density. The Site Catchment
            Analysis used in the framework of GIS revealed over 120 fortified and unfortified settlements of the early
            medieval Alanic tribes. The investigation consisted of several stages in the course of which potential
            ploughing areas were modelled for each settlement. It was based on the combined archaeological and soil
            field survey around fortified settlements in the different parts of the area. It appears that from the fifth
            to the eighth centuries AD relatively flat territories of 1 km round the site were the most valuable for
            agriculture. The rest of the economic area, simulated using Thiessen tessellation, could have been used for
            pasture and hay-making. Computer simulation of the potential economic territories gives the possibility to
            determine the area of proposed ploughing and pasture holdings and to estimate the quantity of settled
            population along with their cattle. As a result, a modelling thesis of a small dimension of the patronymic
            society of the Alans who occupied these early medieval settlements and the affirmation of self-sufficiency
            of their economy were confirmed.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/26</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Early Middle Ages, North Caucasus, GIS, Spatial Analysis, Agriculture</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.3</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>27</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">La Cilicia/Isauria tra IV e metà VII secolo: insediamenti, produzioni e attività
            economiche. Nuove considerazioni alla luce dei più recenti studi sulla regione
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Veronica Iacomi</name>
                <email>veronica.iacomi@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Valentina Cassiani</name>
                <email>valentina.cassiani@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Sapienza Università di Roma, Missione Archeologica Italiana ad Elaiussa
                Sebaste
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Questo contributo si propone di analizzare in maniera organica alcuni dati
            significativi, emersi combinando gli studi delle due autrici, in merito alle trasformazione dei modelli
            urbani e produttivi nella Cilicia Tracheia/Isauria nel periodo tardo romano e protobizantino.
            Da una prima analisi emerge un quadro della regione piuttosto complesso e articolato che vede un territorio
            ricco di centri urbani a cui si alternano aree rurali dedite alla produzione agricola e alla lavorazione
            delle materie prime e che attraversa in questo periodo (IV – metà VII secolo) una fase di evidente
            incremento dell’attività commerciale, proiettando le città della costa dell’Isauria nelle rotte mediterranee
            fino in Occidente. Un tale mutamento nell’assetto economico, però, non può prescindere da una crescita
            dell’attività produttiva che raggiunge una portata inedita e che si manifesta principalmente nella
            coltivazione della vite e dell’ulivo e nella commercializzazione di vino e olio.
            Dal punto di vista archeologico ciò si riscontra, per esempio, nella diffusione sul territorio extraurbano
            di impianti legati principalmente alla produzione di olio e vino e nella presenza considerevole, soprattutto
            in contesti cittadini, di fornaci per la fabbricazione di contenitori da trasporto: la produzione sembra non
            più volta a soddisfare il solo fabbisogno locale, ma razionalizzata in maniera tale da garantire un surplus
            di materie prime destinate al commercio. In questo contesto doveva essere fondamentale il sistema integrato
            aree rurali – città costiere, basato sulla produzione nelle prime e sulla commercializzazione delle merci
            nelle seconde, malgrado resti ancora di difficile comprensione il sistema amministrativo che doveva regolare
            i rapporti tra le due realtà. D’altra parte, nello studio integrato di tali dinamiche si riscontrano ancora
            numerose problematiche che si auspica possano essere superate attraverso l’acquisizione di nuovi dati e
            ulteriori indagini sul territorio.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/27</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Cilicia/Isauria, economia, Elaiussa Sebaste, vino e olio, anfore LR1</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.4</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>28</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">An imperial town in a time of transition. Life, environment, and decline of early
            Byzantine Caričin Grad
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Jago Jonathan Birk</name>
                <email>J.Birk@geo.uni-mainz.de</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Ivan Bugarski</name>
                <email>ivan.bugarski@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Sabine Fiedler</name>
                <email>S.Fiedler@geo.uni-mainz.de</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Vujadin Ivanišević</name>
                <email>vujadin.ivanisevic@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Henriette Kroll</name>
                <email>kroll@rgzm.de</email>
                <affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Nemanja Marković</name>
                <email>nemamarkovic@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Anna Reuter</name>
                <email>reuter@rgzm.de</email>
                <affiliationId>3</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Constanze Röhl</name>
                <email>roehl@rgzm.de</email>
                <affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Rainer Schreg</name>
                <email>schreg@rgzm.de</email>
                <affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Aleksandar Stamenković</name>
                <email>astamenco@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Sonja Stamenković</name>
                <email>sonjas612@yahoo.com</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Miriam Steinborn</name>
                <email>steinborn@rgzm.de</email>
                <affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz</affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Institute of Archaeology Belgrade</affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="2">Römisch-Germanisches Zentralmuseum Mainz</affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="3">Römisch-Germanisches Zentralmuseum Mainz/Instititute of Pre- and
                Protohistory, University of Kiel
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The site of Caričin Grad in south-eastern Serbia – currently listed on UNESCO’s
            tentative list – has been the subject of archaeological investigations for more than 100 years. For the last
            decades it has been the focus of a joint project of the Archaeological Institute in Belgrade and the École
            Française de Rome. A reconstruction of the economic, environmental and social history of the city is the
            main objective of a cooperative project started in 2014 with the Römisch-Germanisches Zentralmuseum Mainz.
            The remains of the early Byzantine complex of Caričin Grad show the features of a city built in the
            classical, Hellenistic-Roman tradition, combined with ecclesiastical Christian architecture. Based on the
            comparison of Byzantine text sources with the settlement’s topography and its architecture, Caričin Grad is
            supposed to be identical to Iustiniana Prima, a city newly founded by the Emperor Justinian as the region’s
            episcopal and administrative centre.
            With the period of occupation covering a mere 90 years, from circa AD 530 to circa AD 615, the site allows a
            rare archaeological “snapshot” of a short period of very intensive use, which furthermore remained
            undisturbed from later encroachments. Due to these circumstances, Caričin Grad offers the unique opportunity
            to analyse a city at the turn of the Late Antique era to the Early Medieval epoch and the complex issues
            associated with periods of cultural transition.
            Based on the perspective of human ecology and social sciences, the project will establish new approaches and
            investigate the concept of “city” during periods of cultural transition by using methods of archaeozoology,
            archaeobotany, geoarchaeology, soil science and GIS.
            The main topic addressed within this context, “Households, consumption and everyday life” will deal with
            single domestic units concerning methods of production, consumption and activity zones regarding comestible
            goods. This perspective on the town and its consumption will be complemented by a viewpoint on the
            surrounding landscape focussing on its resources and agrarian production.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/28</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Urban Archaeology, Household Archaeology, Ecological Archaeology, Environmental Archaeology, Late
                Antiquity
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.5</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>29</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Recapturing the Dynamics of the Early Byzantine Settlements in Crete: Old problems | New
            Interpretations through an Interdisciplinary Approach
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Christina Tsigonaki</name>
                <email>tsigonaki@uoc.gr</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Apostolos Sarris</name>
                <email>asaris@ret.forthnet.gr</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">University of Crete, Department of History and Archaeology &amp;
                Institute of Mediterranean Studies (I.M.S.) - Foundation for Research and Technology (F.O.R.T.H.)
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">GeoSat ReSeArch Lab, Institute of Mediterranean Studies (I.M.S.) -
                Foundation for Research and Technology (F.O.R.T.H.)
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper presents the methodological framework and the first results of a project
            launched in 2014 entitled Recapturing the Dynamics of the Early Byzantine Settlements in Crete: Old problems
            | New Interpretations through an Interdisciplinary Approach. Through an interdisciplinary approach,
            combining a careful reading of historical and archaeological evidence with the spatial analysis offered by
            the application of new technologies in archaeological research, the project highlights the developments of
            Cretan settlements from the fourth century to the early ninth century. In particular, we will examine the
            data categories and discuss how they are brought together for analysis in a Geographical Information System.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/29</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Crete, Early Byzantine Period, Settlement History, Remote Sensing, GIS</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.6</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>30</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Settlement dynamics and site hierarchies in western Sicily from fourth to seventh c. AD:
            interpretative challenges in the Contessa Entellina Survey
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Antonino Facella</name>
                <email>antonino.facella@sns.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Soprintendenza per i Beni Archeologici della Calabria, Italy Scuola
                Normale Superiore di Pisa, Italy
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The Contessa Entellina survey is an intensive and systematic archaeological survey
            carried out in western Sicily, on an area extending over 136.4 km2, out of which more than 114 km2 were
            physically covered. The observation of settlement trends from the fourth to seventh centuries shows, on
            first glance, a noticeable drop in the number of sites from the third to fourth centuries, a new rise in the
            fifth century and a dramatic fall around the end of the century, followed by a period of stability or slow
            decrease throughout the sixth and seventh centuries. A more detailed analysis reveals, on the other hand, a
            much higher density of fifth century diagnostic artefacts (per site and per settled hectare), when compared
            with the previous and the two following centuries. The fifth century is therefore much more “visible” on the
            ground, and this may have contributed to the higher identification of fifth century sites.
            The massive presence of fifth century artefacts may not be exclusively due to a population increase:
            economic and socio-cultural factors most likely also came into play, distorting the resulting settlement
            picture. More precisely, a possible higher tendency towards a grain monoculture may have caused a massive
            import of African foodstuffs (attested by amphorae) between the late fourth and the middle fifth century,
            and peculiar dietary customs could explain the all-pervading diffusion of African Red Slip Ware cups
            belonging to the form Hayes 80-81. Similarly, if we take into consideration also less diagnostic artefacts
            such as roof tiles, we find that the fall in the number of sites between the end of the fifth and the
            sixth-seventh centuries may have been less drastic than it appears, and that it was followed by attempts to
            work out new settlement strategies, showing a fairly good resilience.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/30</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Settlement Trends, Late Antiquity, Sicily, Archaeological Survey, Rural Population</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.7</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>31</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Estrazione e raffinazione dello zolfo e paesaggio nella Sicilia romana tra IV e VI d.C.
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Luca Zambito</name>
                <email>lucazambito@libero.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università di Palermo</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Sulphur was important in several fields: military, tanning, wool’s disinfection and
            many other activities. Nevertheless, the largest quantity of sulphur was used in agriculture, particularly
            in viticulture as it was used to combat fungal diseases especially in wine production areas. Sicily, and in
            particular the area surrounding Agrigento, was the main site of sulphur extraction. This built strong
            relationships with Rome and other agricultural centres in the Mediterranean Sea. Very important among the
            historical sources and the archaeological evidence are the so called Tabulae sulphuris, concerning the
            sulphur exploitation at the Agrigento’s area. Recent finds and studies gave a new chronology dating to a few
            of the tegulae sulphuris and the related sulphur exploitation between the end of the fourth and the sixth
            centuries. It is now possible to attribute to Sicily (in particular, the “area solfifera”) the trade
            relationships which arose in Classical times. We must connect these commercial and cultural ties to the
            export of wheat and other commodities. The main goal of this paper is to show new data on the exploitation
            structures and the transformation of the mining landscape between Late Antiquity and the Byzantine Age.
            During this time, Agrigentum lost its function as fiscal centre, maybe because other centres were acquiring
            this role.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/31</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Sulfur Exploitation and Trade, Ancient Landscape, Survey, Roman Economy, Roman Sicily</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.8</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>32</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Changes and Transformations of the Spatial Structure and Landscape in the Area of L’Aquila
            between the Fourth and Eighth Centuries AD
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Fabio Redi</name>
                <email>fabio.redi@cc.univaq.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università degli Studi dell’Aquila, Department of Humanities
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">In the period between Late Antiquity and the Early Middle Ages, the territory of
            L’Aquila underwent a number of transformations that also occurred elsewhere. The cities (Amiternum, Civita
            di Bagno, Peltuinum, Aufinum) suffered a heavy setback in their urban and economic development because of
            the general crisis of the Empire, the devastating effects of earthquakes in the second half of the fourth
            century, the Greek-Gothic war, the barbarian migrations and last, but not least, the changes in society and
            the ideological-cultural transformation induced by Christianisation. The relationship between town and
            country / city and territory undergoes fundamental changes, with different connotations in terms of
            landscape and settlements. The archaeological research and excavation of the surface, which we have carried
            out in the territory of L’Aquila for over a decade, is beginning to provide evidence of the results of the
            urban and rural landscape transformations: the Christianisation of space and functional transformation of
            major public and private facilities are confirmed by the discovery of churches replacing temples, as in
            Centurelli and in Piana San Marco and so on. Other evidence is provided by citadels obtained through the
            restoration of theatres and amphitheatres or city gates, as in the restorations and transformations of
            Peltuinum and Amiternum. We can also mention functional transformations such as private domus, sometimes
            with a long occupation of public spaces, such as in Amiternum and Peltuinum, or the defunctionalisation of
            infrastructures such as thermal complexes, roads, aqueducts and sewers. Homes or wooden cabins occupy the
            scene in the Amiternum theatre; churches like Santa Maria of Ansedonia abut the city walls. The rural
            landscape is changing for many reasons: the spread of Christian places of worship, the collapsing of public
            infrastructures such as roads or waterways, the advancement of wetlands and uncultivated areas and grazing
            activities to the detriment of agricultural areas. By the seventh century there is a further change in urban
            and agro-pastoral planning, which will be illustrated with concrete examples provided by the archaeological
            research we are carrying out.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/32</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>L’Aquila, Changes and Transformations, Settlement Patterns, Landscapes, Fourth-Eighth Centuries
                AD
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.9</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>33</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Roman Order and Early Christian Redefinition: Crossed Archeological and Anthropological
            Analysis from Riva del Garda (TN)
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Cristina Bassi</name>
                <email>cristina.bassi@provincia.tn.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Valeria Amoretti</name>
                <email>valeamoretti@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Ufficio Beni Archeologici, Soprintendenza Beni Culturali, Trento
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Dipartimento di Architettura e Disegno Industriale, Seconda Università
                degli Studi di Napoli
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper draws its origin from a series of archaeological interventions led by the
            Soprintendenza per i Beni Archeologici della provincia Autonoma di Trento under the supervision of Cristina
            Bassi in the area called “piana Benacense”, a fertile plain near Riva del Garda, in the northern part of
            Lake Garda. The results of the excavation that took place in San Cassiano (2005-2006) are debated along with
            related anthropological studies. The site, placed beside the current Via Marone, follows the layout of an
            ancient Roman street characterised by the presence of burial areas. The area, about 6000 m2, presented the
            existence of a road that divided a Roman villa from two separated burial areas (dated respectively to the
            third and fourth centuries AD). The Roman villa, with structures that are dated from the first to the fourth
            centuries AD, included a large productive area better identified after the anthropological analysis of the
            individuals buried in the southern necropolis. In this area there were both incinerations and inhumations
            graves, all characterised by the same markers of osteological stress compatible to wool manufacturing. The
            smaller northern burial area was built for wealthier people, sometimes showing the traces of similar work
            activities. In the fifth-sixth centuries the landscape totally changed and a church was built, hosting a few
            high-status graves. The analysis of human remains revealed that all the individuals were males and showed
            the so-called “horseman syndrome” with some trauma fractures. We suppose that this leading group
            commissioned the church. After the fifth century, data agree upon a generalised implosion of economic
            structures, as confirmed by the markers of occupational stress on bones. Therefore the crossing of
            archeological and anthropological results trace the landscape history of the Benacense plain, from the
            well-organised and productive Roman period to a period lacking organisation and economic structures. This is
            the reason San Cassiano could be considered a significant component for the historical reconstruction of the
            Garda area in “the time of change”.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/33</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Riva del Garda Area, Anthropological Analysis, Transition Era, Early Christianisation, Landscape
                Use
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.10</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>34</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">The Early Christian Sanctuaries and the Transformation of Italian Landscape</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Alessandro Luciano</name>
                <email>alessandro.luciano@beniculturali.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università degli Studi di Napoli Suor Orsola Benincasa</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">In the early Christian period the birth and development of relics’ cult led to the
            transformation of urban, suburban and rural Italian landscape. Indeed, the deposition of venerated bodies in
            extra-muros cemeteries led to the gradual Christianisation of the whole peninsula. The link between
            territories and martyrs’ cults is shown by Christian Calendars, which reported just the dies natalis and the
            place of depositio. The saints were so territorially well established that their burials were simply
            considered as loca by ancient Christians. The gradual monumentalisation of martyrs’ tombs led to the birth
            of huge sanctuaries. They were composed of funerary and religious buildings but also service facilities,
            accommodations for pilgrims and monasteries. The most important sanctuaries were those of Saints Peter in
            the Vatican, Erasmus in Formia, Alexander in Nomentum, Felix in Cimitile, Januarius in Naples, Felix in
            Venosa, Marcianus in Syracuse and the Apostles in Concordia. They became so popular that Jerome said:
            ‘movetur urbs sedibus suis’. It seems that sometimes there was a coincidence between sanctuaries and
            episcopal palaces, such as in Sardinia, in some part of Latium and probably at Cimitile, Venosa and
            Concordia Sagittaria. In the fifth and sixth centuries some sanctuaries spread also in rural areas, usually
            along important routes. Suburban and rural sanctuaries led to the development of new settlements, as shown
            by the birth of new villages. The current word “Cimitile”, for example, derives from “Cimiterium” and even
            Paulinus of Nola wrote about a vicus nearby the sanctuary. At Saint Peter’s tomb, a Civitas was born in the
            Early Middle Ages. At the end of the Early Christian era, the traslationes broke the tie between relics and
            their locus depositionis, causing new urban sanctuaries to form.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/34</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Christian Sanctuaries, Relics, Saints, Basilicas, Graves</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.11</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>35</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">The Transformation and Christianisation of Urban Landscapes in Central Lusitania during
            Late Antiquity and the Early Middle Ages: the Cases of Ammaia and Ebora Iulia
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Emilia Gallo</name>
                <email>gallo.emilia@libero.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Department of Human Sciences, University of l’Aquila, Italy
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This research focuses on the process of late transformation and final abandonment of
            Roman towns, on the Christianisation phenomenon and on the late antique evolution of settlement patterns in
            central Lusitania. The traditional explanations of sudden abandonments of Roman centres, due to “external”
            events, were swept away by a more scientific approach to archaeological evidence. The article presents data
            on the Late Antiquity phases of Ammaia and Ebora Iulia (today Évora). The results of a long period of
            archaeo-topographical research on the deserted Roman town of Ammaia (Marvão, Portugal), supported by
            international scientific collaborations, disclose new scenarios. On the basis of the survey data, integrated
            with the results of the recent ground-truthing excavations, it is possible to state that, from the beginning
            of the fourth century AD, the town seemed to be interested in a process of transformation and not of
            degradation. Évora was a bigger town and it was, from the fourth century AD, the seat of the diocese. In
            fact, it was one of the first towns of Lusitania and its bishop was present at the Council of Elvira
            (306/314 AD). Évora, unlike Ammaia, had continuity of occupation and therefore archaeological research has
            to deal with the problems usually connected with urban archaeology. The intention is to draw a short summary
            about the transformations that characterise the two towns in this period and, finally, identify common
            elements and differences.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/35</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Christianisation, Lusitania, Transformations, Urban Landscapes, Rural Landscapes.</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.12</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>36</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Epilogue: In Search of an Identity: Landscape Archaeology for Post-Classical Studies.
            Defining and Understanding Archaeological Landscapes
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Cristina Corsi</name>
                <email>c.corsi@unicas.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Department of Humanities, University of Cassino, Italy</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/36</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords/>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.13</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>37</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Archaeomorphology as Landscape Archaeology: New Approaches and Perspectives</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Hector A. Orengo</name>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Josep M. Palet</name>
                <email>jpalet@icac.cat</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">McDonald Institute for Archaeological Research, University of Cambridge.
                Downing Street, CB2 3ER, Cambridge, UK
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Landscape Archaeology Research Group (GIAP), Catalan Institute of
                Classical Archaeology (ICAC)
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Archaeomorphology, the study of human-made landscape forms such as roads, field
            systems, terraces, water channels, etc. is an important part of landscape studies. The archaeological
            features studied through archaeomorphological approaches display a long-term chronology and play an
            important role in the configuration of human habitat, movement and sustenance. In many cases, this role can
            still be appreciated in today’s cultural landscapes. However, during the last decades the
            archaeomorphological study of centuriations and other field systems has been considered a marginal and
            unscientific discipline. This is largely due to the multiplication of unreliable archaeomorphological
            studies on centuriations developed from the 70s to the 90s, some of which have been proved wrong by
            large-scale archaeological excavations. Nonetheless, the last decade has seen a revival of centuriation and
            other archaeomorphology-based studies. Events such as the 2009 international conference The application of
            centurial systems and methods of agrarian organisation from the Roman period to the early Middle Ages or the
            publication of Agri Centuriati, an International Journal of Landscape Archaeology beginning in 2004 have
            helped to put this discipline “back on the map”.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/37</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Archaeomorphology, Landscape Archaeology, Road Networks, Centuriation, Cultural Landscapes.
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.14</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>38</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">The Landscapes of the Ancient Appia Project: Formation and Degeneration Processes in
            Landscapes Stratification of the Benevento Area.
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Alessandro Terribile</name>
                <email>a.terribile85@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Cristiano Benedetto De Vita</name>
                <email>cr.devita@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">University of Salerno, Dipartimento di Scienze del Patrimonio Culturale,
                Salerno, Italia
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Università degli Studi di Salerno, Dipartimento di Scienze dei Beni
                Culturali, Salerno, Italia
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">In this work we intend to illustrate methods and tools used for evaluating and defining
            some of the post-depositional processes of the archaeological record in the Eastern Beneventan landscapes.
            Our research aims especially to recognise the traces of the “longue durée” phenomena, highlighting what may
            be considered a result of the past still observable in the present. Which are the tools that allow us to
            identify landscapes marks, anthropogenic and environmental processes responsible of the survival or,
            conversely, of the obliteration of the ancient forms? A first approach attempts to create a dialogic
            relationship with the historical cartographic documents (such as ancient cadastres, notarial instruments,
            boundary disputes) and sheds light on the dynamics of the perceptible transformations of landscapes,
            bringing back an overall view of their contextual distinctive traits. This ensures the identification of
            “ecofacts” and “artefacts” that contributes to the structuration of the landscapes that have occurred over
            time as stratified units. A second procedure involves the reading of the historical information combined
            with the environmental one, through an archaeomorphological approach. The study has provided an overlap
            among the ancient and modern rural fabrics (for example roads, canals, talwegs, agrarian boundaries) and the
            geomorphological dynamics, with the aim of discerning the forms of degradation and to define, when possible,
            a relative chronology. Such an approach evaluates the distribution of surface artefacts and their spatial
            and temporal characteristics, enabling recording of the higher or lower level of degradation in the
            archaeological record, emphasising those landscapes units considered of high information potential.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/38</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Benevento, Ancient Appia Landscapes, Historical Cartography, Archaeomorphology, Post-Depositional
                Processes.
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.15</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>39</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">L’analisi archeomorfologica delle reti viarie come studio delle dinamiche evolutive del
            paesaggio. Il caso della bassa pianura veneta tra Padova e Rovigo
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Michele Matteazzi</name>
                <email>michele.matteazzi@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Catalan Institute of Classical Archaeology (ICAC) - Grup d’Investigació
                en Arqueologia del Paisatge (GIAP) Plaça d’en Rovellat s/N; 43003 Tarragona, Spain
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">In this paper we analyse the contribution that archaeomorfological analysis of road
            networks can bring to the study of landscape dynamics, focusing on the study case of the low Venetian plain
            between Padua and Rovigo. Methodologically, we found our work on a study published by Eric Vion in 1989
            where, for the first time, the Swiss scholar defended the importance of the morphological study of
            communication routes to understand the historical evolution of a territory. By applying the basic principles
            of this method, we have analysed the territory in order to highlight its main evolutionary stages.
            So we could establish that, after a series of interventions dating back to Protohistoric times, the first
            real large-scale landscape structuration was carried out by the Romans, initially (second century BC) by
            drafting a series of extra regional routes designed to connect the northernmost colony of Aquileia with the
            southern strongholds of Ariminum, Mutina, and Bononia and, later (first century BC-first century AD), by
            implementing the road network through the realization of new routes and at least three different centuriated
            field systems in the territories controlled by Patavium, Ateste and Atria.
            With the fall of the Roman Empire during Late Antiquity, all these infrastructures had to be partly
            abandoned and partly re-functionalized by seconding the changed needs of the rural population. Around the
            10th century, it seems possible to date the first setting of a series of so-called radial systems that
            deeply modify the previous centurial infrastructures, while between 11th and 13th centuries, a series of
            interventions on the road network were promoted by the city of Padua. Finally, from fifteenth to eighteenth
            century, new interventions (construction of new roads and channels and reclamation works) were carried out,
            especially in the lagoon area, by the government of Venice Republic.
            In this paper we analyse the contribution that archaeomorfological analysis of road networks can bring to
            the study of landscape dynamics, focusing on the study case of the low Venetian plain between Padua and
            Rovigo. Methodologically, we found our work on a study published by Eric Vion in 1989 where, for the first
            time, the Swiss scholar defended the importance of the morphological study of communication routes to
            understand the historical evolution of a territory. By applying the basic principles of this method, we have
            analysed the territory in order to highlight its main evolutionary stages.
            So we could establish that, after a series of interventions dating back to Protohistoric times, the first
            real large-scale landscape structuration was carried out by the Romans, initially (second century BC) by
            drafting a series of extra regional routes designed to connect the northernmost colony of Aquileia with the
            southern strongholds of Ariminum, Mutina, and Bononia and, later (first century BC-first century AD), by
            implementing the road network through the realization of new routes and at least three different centuriated
            field systems in the territories controlled by Patavium, Ateste and Atria.
            With the fall of the Roman Empire during Late Antiquity, all these infrastructures had to be partly
            abandoned and partly re-functionalized by seconding the changed needs of the rural population. Around the
            10th century, it seems possible to date the first setting of a series of so-called radial systems that
            deeply modify the previous centurial infrastructures, while between 11th and 13th centuries, a series of
            interventions on the road network were promoted by the city of Padua. Finally, from fifteenth to eighteenth
            century, new interventions (construction of new roads and channels and reclamation works) were carried out,
            especially in the lagoon area, by the government of Venice Republic.
            In this paper we analyse the contribution that archaeomorfological analysis of road networks can bring to
            the study of landscape dynamics, focusing on the study case of the low Venetian plain between Padua and
            Rovigo. Methodologically, we found our work on a study published by Eric Vion in 1989 where, for the first
            time, the Swiss scholar defended the importance of the morphological study of communication routes to
            understand the historical evolution of a territory. By applying the basic principles of this method, we have
            analysed the territory in order to highlight its main evolutionary stages.
            So we could establish that, after a series of interventions dating back to Protohistoric times, the first
            real large-scale landscape structuration was carried out by the Romans, initially (second century BC) by
            drafting a series of extra regional routes designed to connect the northernmost colony of Aquileia with the
            southern strongholds of Ariminum, Mutina, and Bononia and, later (first century BC-first century AD), by
            implementing the road network through the realization of new routes and at least three different centuriated
            field systems in the territories controlled by Patavium, Ateste and Atria.
            With the fall of the Roman Empire during Late Antiquity, all these infrastructures had to be partly
            abandoned and partly re-functionalized by seconding the changed needs of the rural population. Around the
            10th century, it seems possible to date the first setting of a series of so-called radial systems that
            deeply modify the previous centurial infrastructures, while between 11th and 13th centuries, a series of
            interventions on the road network were promoted by the city of Padua. Finally, from fifteenth to eighteenth
            century, new interventions (construction of new roads and channels and reclamation works) were carried out,
            especially in the lagoon area, by the government of Venice Republic.
            In this paper we analyse the contribution that archaeomorfological analysis of road networks can bring to
            the study of landscape dynamics, focusing on the study case of the low Venetian plain between Padua and
            Rovigo. Methodologically, we found our work on a study published by Eric Vion in 1989 where, for the first
            time, the Swiss scholar defended the importance of the morphological study of communication routes to
            understand the historical evolution of a territory. By applying the basic principles of this method, we have
            analysed the territory in order to highlight its main evolutionary stages.
            So we could establish that, after a series of interventions dating back to Protohistoric times, the first
            real large-scale landscape structuration was carried out by the Romans, initially (second century BC) by
            drafting a series of extra regional routes designed to connect the northernmost colony of Aquileia with the
            southern strongholds of Ariminum, Mutina, and Bononia and, later (first century BC-first century AD), by
            implementing the road network through the realization of new routes and at least three different centuriated
            field systems in the territories controlled by Patavium, Ateste and Atria.
            With the fall of the Roman Empire during Late Antiquity, all these infrastructures had to be partly
            abandoned and partly re-functionalized by seconding the changed needs of the rural population. Around the
            10th century, it seems possible to date the first setting of a series of so-called radial systems that
            deeply modify the previous centurial infrastructures, while between 11th and 13th centuries, a series of
            interventions on the road network were promoted by the city of Padua. Finally, from fifteenth to eighteenth
            century, new interventions (construction of new roads and channels and reclamation works) were carried out,
            especially in the lagoon area, by the government of Venice Republic.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/39</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Archaeomorphology</keyword>
            <keyword>Road Networks</keyword>
            <keyword>Landscape Dynamics</keyword>
            <keyword>Low Venetian Plain</keyword>
            <keyword>“longue durée”</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>spa</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.16</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>40</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Más allá de la herencia medieval. Una nueva arqueomorfología para el paisaje histórico de
            Valencia.
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Maria Jesús Ortega</name>
                <email>mjortega@icac.cat</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Hèctor A. Orengo</name>
                <email>hector.orengo@sheffield.ac.uk</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Josep M. Palet</name>
                <email>jpalet@icac.cat</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Grup d’Investigació en Arqueologia del Paisatge (GIAP), Institut Català
                d’Arqueologia Clàssica (ICAC) Plaça Rovellat, s/n. 43003 Tarragona, Spain
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">McDonald Institute for Archaeological Research, University of Cambridge.
                Downing Street, CB2 3ER, Cambridge, UK
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The historic territory of Valencia is being analysed in the frame of a new research
            project, Valentia Landscape Project, aiming to characterise the dynamics of the Valencian Cultural Landscape
            from the Iron Age (seventh - sixth century BC) to the Modern period. An important part of the project is
            focused on Antiquity and one of its major goals is reviewing through a new archaeomorphological analysis,
            the ancient road network, in order to study historical field systems and to analyse the centuriation
            hypothesis proposed up to now. The archaeomorphological analysis has allowed us to propose new hypothesis
            about the origin and dynamics of the Valencian Cultural Landscape. In this sense, the study has attested the
            presence, in the present landscape, of many axes whose origin is related to the Roman centuriated road
            system. Multidisciplinarity and a long-term approach have brought a high level of precision to this work’s
            results.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/40</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Cultural landscape, Valencia, Archaeomorphology, Road Network, GIS</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.17</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>41</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">The Identification of Land Divisions in the Ancient Mediterranean through Integrated
            Remote Sensing and GIS Applications
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Jamieson C. Donati</name>
                <email>jcdonati@ims.forth.gr</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Laboratory of Geophysical, Satellite Remote Sensing and
                Archaeoenvironment, Institute for Mediterranean Studies, Foundation for Research and Technology, Hellas
                Melissinou and Nikiforou Foka 130, 74100 Rethymno, Crete, Greece
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper explores the advantages of using satellite remote sensing and GIS to
            identify ancient land divisions in the eastern Mediterranean by studying the organisation of modern agrarian
            landscapes. Since current land divisions sometimes retain the arrangement of an older system, either wholly
            or partially, remote sensing methodologies have been successful in distinguishing ancient demarcations,
            especially Roman centuriation. This study places emphasis on techniques to recover past landscapes around
            settlements where the correlation between modern agrarian divisions and a potential ancient system is not
            clear from visual interpretation. Within GIS the dominant orientations of modern agrarian fields are
            analysed and presented as histograms which show general trends in the organisation of land. These
            methodologies are applied in two case-studies where the evidence for an ancient urban or rural land division
            is not well-defined: Mantinea, a classical Greek city in the Peloponnese, and Aphrodisias, a Late
            Hellenistic foundation in western Anatolia. The histograms identify trends in the organisation of modern
            fields that might mark the presence of an ancient system of land demarcation. The data from Mantinea show
            that the majority of modern agricultural fields inside the fortification walls have dominant orientations
            identical to the alignments of excavated buildings and a series of streets revealed through geophysical
            survey. Likewise, there is evidence at Aphrodisias that rural land outside the fortification walls share
            orientations with urban features inside the city. Both examples show that an analysis of the dominant angle
            frequency of modern land divisions is useful for reconstructing the archaeomorphology of ancient landscapes
            in the eastern Mediterranean.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/41</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Remote Sensing, GIS, Urban History, Land Division, Mediterranean Archaeology</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>fre</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.18</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>42</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Le SIG comme outil de détection et d’analyse des parcellaires antiques</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Maxime Seguin</name>
                <email>maxime.seguin@inrap.fr</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Institut National de Recherches Archéologiques Préventives
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The French Rhône valley has traces of ancient roman parcels, testified by antique land
            registers called “Orange cadastre”. This organisation was highlighted on the left bank of the river and it
            seems to extend to the other side, in the Tave and Cèze valleys. All this research was conducted in the 80s
            from the French National Institute of Cartography (IGN) aerial missions using the method of optical
            filtering. In this study, we intend to use a GIS and the cadastral map in vector format (BDParcellaire®
            product from IGN).
            Indeed, the cadastre enables the study of boundaries that have no materialisation in the current landscape.
            The aerial photographs or topographical maps only give incomplete information, i.e. the perennial human
            forms or roads, paths, fences, channels, ditches. These documents are selective. The tool used in this study
            is the histogram of directions. It consists in calculating the azimuth of each parcel boundary and drawing a
            histogram. The number of boundaries or their total length is shown as a function of the azimuth.
            The interests of working with the cadastre are that all information are contained in these documents, their
            precision allows a detailed study of cadastral frames. This method was first validated on previously studied
            areas and then extended to the Cèze and Tave lower valleys. This helped to detect the presence of “Orange
            cadastre” in these two valleys, where the method by optical filtering had not delivered convincing results.
            The use of these vector data for the detection of ancient cadastral frames permits a detailed study of the
            boundaries structure. The results are encouraging and allow the consideration of new approaches. It would be
            interesting to combine elevation and topographic data as well as ancient “Napoleonic cadastre” with the aim
            to eliminate nineteenth and twentieth century boundaries.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/42</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>GIS, Land Registers, Histogram of Directions, Vector Cadastral Map, Orange Cadastre</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>spa</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.19</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>43</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Paths and settlement in a Roman rural landscape: An archaeomorphological analysis in the
            Congost Valley (Barcelona, Spain) / Trazas viarias y poblamiento en un paisaje rural romano: análisis
            arqueomorfológico en el valle del río Congost (Barcelona)
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Arnau Garcia</name>
                <email>agarcia@icac.cat</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Josep M. Palet</name>
                <email>jpalet@icac.cat</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Marta Flórez</name>
                <email>mflorez_giap@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Landscape Archaeology Research Group (GIAP), Catalan Institute of
                Classical Archaeology (ICAC) Plaça Rovellat, s/n. 43003 Tarragona, Spain
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Landscape Archaeology Research Group (GIAP), Catalan Institute of
                Classical Archaeology (ICAC)
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The territorial organisation of rural areas in the context of the Roman Empire is a
            widely discussed issue in archaeomorphological research but it is also a topic of great interest for the
            study of long-term landscapes dynamics. Most of these studies deal with large territorial management works
            related to known ancient cities. In this paper we propose a discussion about a study case carried out on a
            much more reduced scale, focused in a small river valley, placed in an inland area near Barcelona in the
            North-Eastern sector of the Iberian Peninsula. In this research both the analysis of road network from
            aerial photographs and the study of settlement patterns from the Archaeological Heritage database are
            complemented by fieldwork, survey and the regressive analysis of historical maps. A geomorphological study
            of the area is actually in progress. A significant relationship has been highlighted between an ancient
            Roman road and an intensive settlement network along this historical road axis. Settlement distribution
            along the studied stretch seems to show a pattern related to well-known measures used in Roman land-surveys.
            According to the chronology of these sites, this spatial organisation may coincide with the consolidation
            processes of a Roman urban network at the Tarraconensis province. This process took place during the first
            century BC, especially from the second half of that century. In this paper, the results will be discussed
            and analysed in order to understand how far the data available allow us to interpret landscape organisation
            in relation to geomorphological and environmental dynamics.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/43</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Road Network, Settlement, Rural Landscape, Archeomorphology, Land Survey, Congost River</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.20</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>44</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Archaeomorphology and Agrimensores: problem or opportunity?</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Saskia Roselaar</name>
                <email>saskiaroselaar@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Independent scholar</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper argues that the works of the Agrimensores are of value in studying the
            practicalities of land measurement in the Roman world. It discusses ways in which the Agrimensores might be
            used, not only based on a strict literal reading of the texts, but on the practical circumstances in which
            these works could be used. The paper combines the statements of the Agrimensores with evidence from Roman
            literary and legal sources and from archaeology. It uses the colony Arausio, modern Orange in southern
            France, as a case study.
            The paper concludes that the works of the Agrimensores was based on real situations, examples of which can
            be found in the map of Arausio. The Agrimensores therefore attempted to give general instructions based on
            situations they had encountered in the field. Sometimes these seem overly schematic or abstract, but this
            matches the style of Roman legal writing. It is true that the works of the Agrimensores have often been
            misused in scholarly research, but the paper argues that these texts can be of great value when used in
            combination with archaeological evidence and other legal and technical texts. Thus, these works can be used
            to gain a better understanding of the practicalities of Roman land measurement.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/44</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Agrimensores, Arausio, centuriation, land disputes, incolae.</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.21</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>45</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Archaeology of Commons: a Multidisciplinary Approach to the Reconstruction of Multiple
            Uses and Conflicts on European Uplands
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Anna Maria Stagno</name>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Research Group on Cultural Heritage and Landscapes (University of the
                Basque Country), Laboratory of Environmental Archaeology and History - LASA (Dafist-Distav, University
                of Genoa).
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The paper presents a multidisciplinary research project (“Archaeology of Commons:
            cultural Heritage and Material Evidence of a Disappearing Europe”) on the archaeology of common-lands. The
            main goal of the project is to investigate, by means of historical and archaeological analysis, the intimate
            social dimension at the base of the common lands management in the context of southern European mountainous
            regions. Research investigates the dynamic nature of commons starting from the reconstruction of the present
            organisation of common lands, going back to the complex transformations of common properties in the
            nineteenth century and analysing the problem of the archaeological visibility of conflicts since the ancien
            régime. The project will examine how archaeological methods could clarify different aspects of the history
            of the collective access rights to land, by applying in selected mountain areas methodological approaches
            based on historical ecology, rural and agrarian archaeology.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/45</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Archaeology, Common-Lands, Conflicts, Environmental Resources, Appropriation</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.22</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>46</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Archaeomorphological and Geological Studies on the Ancient Appian Way at the Aurunci Pass:
            Multidisciplinary Approaches for the Investigation of Ancient Quarries Siting and Exploitation.
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Paola Carfora</name>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Emiliano Di Luzio</name>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Seconda Università di Napoli, Dipartimento di Lettere e Beni Culturali
                Piazza San Francesco, 81055, Santa Maria Capua Vetere (Caserta)
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">CNR-ITABC, Istituto per le Tecnologie Applicate ai Beni Culturali Via
                Salaria Km 29.3, 00015, Monterotondo (Rome)
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">An exploitation system of rock quarries was investigated along a tract of the ancient
            Appian Way extending between the modern villages of Itri and Fondi (central Italy). Three new quarries
            carved into carbonatic slopes were discovered through interpretation of aerial photography and
            photogrammetric restitution (this last still in progress) nearby a few extraction areas already acknowledged
            in previous works. Later, field surveys confirmed the anthropogenic nature of slope cuts as inferred from
            squared or rectangular morphological edges and evidence of regular tool-marks. Quarries location and
            exploitation techniques were analysed in relation to the archaeological requirements for the road
            construction and maintenance and also considering the geological setting of the area. In particular, it was
            demonstrated how geometric characteristics of rock masses – such as bedding and joint system spacing or
            intensity of brittle deformation – played a fundamental role in determining the kind of extracted material
            and use of different exploitation techniques. Indeed, cubic and pseudo-cubic rock blocks were extracted from
            quarries A and B during the Roman Age, as evidenced by peculiar tool-marks observed on the rock slope edges
            and tracing intersecting joint system. Quarry C was instead an open-pit derived from a cataclastic rock
            volume in the hanging-wall of a main normal fault and from which centimetres-sized debris were derived. The
            present study set the basis for a further analysis of the local exploitation system which may include other
            minor quarries used for road maintenance works and construction of other buildings.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/46</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Landscape Archaeology, Geomorphology, Quarry Exploitation, Ancient Appian Route, Italy</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.23</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>47</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Tumulus Culture Burial Mounds in the Landscape - Krotoszyn Forest Area: the Beginnings of
            a New Project.
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Mateusz Stróżyk</name>
                <email>mateusz.strozyk@muzarp.poznan.pl</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Poznań Archaeological Museum, Wodna 27 st., 61-781 Poznań, Poland,
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The project presented in this paper is concerned with the funeral rite of the Tumulus
            cultural community located on the border of Silesia and Greater Poland. Detailed multi-disciplinary analyses
            have been applied to a unique slice of the Bronze Age cultural landscape preserved within the cover of a
            100-year old oak forest known as the Krotoszyn Forest. Preliminary research carried out by the author
            (rescue excavations, non-invasive prospection and airborne laser scanning) revealed the existence of 120
            barrows, which are likely to be associated with the dominance of the Tumulus Culture in areas of south-west
            Poland. The information obtained by previous studies was included in the spatial database available to the
            author. It provides basic information on the location, state of preservation and the amount of burial mounds
            in the area of the Krotoszyn Forest. The main aim of the project is to carry out multi-dimensional spatial
            analysis in order to capture the relationship between the variables governing the environment and Tumulus
            Culture burials. The methodological approach adopted by the project consists of the GIS analysis of data
            obtained from the airborne laser scanning, palaeoenvironmental studies and the application of geophysical
            prospection. The project’s targets include the development of an interpretative model able to explain the
            rules of location and strategies of construction of the funeral space of the Tumulus Culture community. The
            proposed models will be drawn upon theoretical reflections related to the concept of landscape archaeology.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/47</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Tumulus Culture, Landscape Archaeology, Spatial Analyses, Middle Bronze Age, Geoarchaeology.
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.24</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>48</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">L’antico sistema delle acque nella Valle della Caffarella</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Angela Paolini</name>
                <email>angela.paolini@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Fabrizio Piccari</name>
                <email>f.piccari@parcoappiaantica.it</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università degli Studi di Roma Tor Vergata</affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Ente Regionale Parco dell’Appia Antica</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">La valle della Caffarella ricade all’interno del Parco Regionale dell’Appia Antica e si
            trova al di fuori delle Mura Aureliane, tra la via Latina e via dell’Appia Antica, tagliata verso sud da via
            dell’Almone. La valle di origine alluvionale è costituita da pianori sommitali tufacei, versanti leggermente
            scoscesi ed un fondovalle ricco di falde acquifere e di numerose sorgenti di acque minerali.
            Particolarmente rilevante è la presenza del fiume Almone sacro ai Romani, ancora oggi terzo fiume di Roma
            per portata, e dei fossi alimentati dalle numerose sorgenti locali, note già in epoca romana. Anticamente
            nella valle della Caffarella si sviluppava un reticolo idrografico molto più complesso di quello attuale. Le
            originarie aree paludose connaturate alla geomorfologia della valle, sono state bonificate nel corso dei
            secoli tramite una serie di opere idrauliche, come canali di convogliamento e drenaggio di varie epoche o la
            creazione in età moderna di fossi scaricatori regolati da chiuse detti anche “marrane” o “incastri”. Molti
            di questi manufatti sono visibili o rintracciabili ancora oggi nella valle e testimoniano le numerose
            attività antropiche realizzate per il controllo delle acque in superficie.
            Mettendo insieme le informazioni ottenute da cartografia storica, foto aeree, sopralluoghi e documentazione
            degli scavi archeologici recenti, si può offrire un contributo alla ricostruzione della idrografia storica
            di questo lembo di campagna romana di grande interesse ambientale e storico archeologico (fig. 1).
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/48</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Appia Antica</keyword>
            <keyword>Valle della Caffarella</keyword>
            <keyword>cartografia storica</keyword>
            <keyword>idrografia storica</keyword>
            <keyword>zone umide</keyword>
            <keyword>rilievo fotogrammetrico.</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.25</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>49</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Intrasite Artefact Survey at Terravecchia di Cuti (Sicily)</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Oscar Belvedere</name>
                <email>oscar.belvedere@unipa.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Aurelio Burgio</name>
                <email>aurelio.burgio@unipa.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università di Palermo, Dipartimento Culture e Società</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">In this paper,we discuss the results of an artefact survey and a sampling collection in
            the indigenous settlement of Terravecchia di Cuti, in the chora of the Greek colony of Himera (Sicily). The
            whole area of the town was gridded with squares of 10x10 m to isolate functional areas and identify the most
            interesting zones for new archaeological samples. The survey was carried out in two fields (9400 m2),
            counting and recording all findings. Only diagnostic pottery and figured pottery, antefixes, loom weights,
            millstones and so on were collected. We can observe, analysing in detail our results for both fields, that
            functional areas could not be isolated, perhaps because the urban and social organisation of the settlement
            did not provide for clear distinctions. The multi-functionality of everyday objects, also, does not allow us
            to recognise these areas. Finally, we must consider the effect of decades of ploughing carried out on the
            site.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/49</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Sicily, Intrasite, Survey</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.26</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>50</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Turlough Hill – Place-making and Mountains in Prehistoric Ireland</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Stefan Bergh</name>
                <email>stefan.bergh@nuigalway.ie</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">School of Geography and Archaeology, National University or Ireland
                Galway,
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Mountains and high ground are often venerated as special places. It is their enigmatic
            quality as elevated ground, their prominence and permanence in both the mental and physical landscapes that
            draws us to them. In this paper the role of mountains in current landscape archaeology is discussed based on
            their role as places of significance in both “visible” and “invisible” landscapes. The conspicuous mountain
            of Turlough Hill, in the Burren, Co. Clare has on its summit a unique group of prehistoric remains
            consisting of some 140 circular houses, a large burial cairn, a multi-vallate enclosure as well as an
            extraordinary hexagonal stone enclosure. Why did people choose this particular mountaintop as the focus for
            this extraordinary activity in prehistory? To answer this question, and to elucidate the wider question of
            the significance of high ground, as well as aspects of place-making, the role of Turlough Hill in prehistory
            is discussed based on the character of the archaeological remains, but also on the character of the mountain
            itself and its location in the wider landscape.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/50</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Landscape Archaeology, Place-making, Sacred Mountain, Liminality, Prehistoric Round House</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.27</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>51</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Contributo alla carta archeologica di Ruvo di Puglia e del suo territorio</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Giovina Caldarola</name>
                <email>giovina.caldarola@unisalento.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Laboratorio di Topografia Antica e Fotogrammetria (LabTAF), Università
                del Salento, Lecce, Italy
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Ruvo di Puglia is located in the continuity of life in central Puglia. It stands on a
            hill located between the area Murgia and the Adriatic coast. The first traces of the area date back to the
            Middle and Upper Paleolithic and the phase is documented peuceta with numerous monumental tombs with rich
            graves. At the beginning of the third century BC, Ruvo becomes a member before becoming municipium after the
            social war. The survival of the city was guaranteed by the Via Minucia which connected Benevento to Brindisi
            through Puglia. This road will become the Traiana in Imperial times, ensuring continuity of life in the
            city. Nevertheless, the town lost its hegemony and was greatly reduced. One of the few pieces of epigraphic
            evidence of Roman attests to the presence of a surrounding wall of which no trace remains: what is preserved
            material dates from the Aragonese domination. The attention is focused on the origins of Ruvo in the early
            nineteenth century, following the random discoveries of rich grave peuceta. This phenomenon contributes to
            wage a “excavations fever” and plundering of a necropolis with consequent destruction of the ancient urban
            fabric. Encouraged by Borbonic Government, the results of these excavations went to increase the actual
            collection of the Museum Borbonico of Naples and private collections around the world.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/51</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Peucetians, Illegal Excavations, Roman Roads, Archaeological Map, Continuity of Life of a City
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.28</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>52</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">The Archaeological Map for the Reconstruction of the Ancient Topography of the Greek and
            Roman City of Taormina
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Lorenzo Campagna</name>
                <email>lorenzo.campagna@unime.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Giuseppe Scardozzi</name>
                <email>g.scardozzi@ibam.cnr.it</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">University of Messina, Department of Ancient and Modern Cultures,
                Messina
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">National Research Council of Italy – Institute for Archaeological and
                Monumental Heritage, Lecce
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">TResearch is aimed at the production of a tool that could be useful both for the
            reconstruction of the ancient urban planning and its development during the Greek, Roman and Medieval ages,
            and for the management and preservation of the archaeological heritage of Taormina; in fact, the new
            archaeological map could be included in policies aimed at an urban development that respects the existing
            ancient remains and promotes their enhancement of value.
            The paper concerns the research project started in 2009 and aimed at the production of the archaeological
            map of Tauromenion/Tauromenium, on which the modern Taormina lies. The project is carried out by the
            Department of Ancient and Modern Cultures of the University of Messina and the Institute for Archaeological
            and Monumental Heritage of the Italian National Research Council, with the cooperation of the Archaeological
            Superintendence of the Province of Messina and the Archaeological Park of Giardini Naxos.
            The research project involves a context characterised by a long continuity of life during centuries and it
            is based on:
            1) archaeological and topographical surveys using a differential GPS system and a total station;
            2) systematic study and analysis of archival documentation, previous bibliographies and historical
            cartographies;
            3) interpretation of aerial photos, in particular those taken between the years 1920s and 1940s, when some
            sectors of the ancient city and necropolises were not still covered by the extension of the modern town.
            All the collected data were georeferenced in a digital archaeological map, where all the ancient monuments
            and structures, both still visible and those re-buried after small-scale excavations, are integrated on a
            up-to-date large-scale vector cartography. The map is integrated in a web-oriented GIS platform developed
            using open source software and cloud computing solutions; it is aimed at the data management and sharing
            between the different institutions involved in the project.
            Therefore, the research is aimed at the production of a tool that could be useful both for the
            reconstruction of the ancient urban planning and its development during the Greek, Roman and Medieval ages,
            and for the management and preservation of the archaeological heritage of Taormina; in fact, the new
            archaeological map could be included in policies aimed at an urban development that respects the existing
            ancient remains and promotes their enhancement of value.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/52</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Archaeological map</keyword>
            <keyword>Taormina</keyword>
            <keyword>Hellenistic and Roman urbanism</keyword>
            <keyword>WebGIS</keyword>
            <keyword>Preservation.</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.29</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>53</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Mura urbiche nell’Italia centro-settentrionale: significato e funzione tra la fine della
            repubblica e la prima età imperiale
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Dario Canino</name>
                <email>caninodario@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Sapienza Università di Roma</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The text synthesizes an analysis of the meaning and function of city walls through a
            series of examples of urban settlements founded, or renewed, in cental-northern Italy, between the end of
            the Republic and the First Imperial Age. A period in which, in different geographical areas, different
            monumental results were produced. In some cases the need for defense is still relevant and the structure of
            city walls, gates and towers, reveal this need. Despite the Pax Augusta, the phenomenon of brigandage, in
            primis, imposes in some areas a certain attention to their defensive function. In other cases, the city
            walls may have existed to perform functions different than that of defensive; functions that are not limited
            only to a symbolic ritual matrix. In this process, even the city gates are transformed, entering in
            symbiosis with the monumental typology of the honorary arch and becoming, sometimes, a real commemorative
            monument of particular events. The prestige of the location of this monumental typology in the city wall is
            completely independent from the validity of the defensive walls. The city walls interact with the doors and
            with the towers both functionally and formally. Now, their task is not to close the village in a rigid
            internal/external alternative but rather to create a dialogue between the reality of the settlement and what
            surrounds it. This dialogue takes place, thanks to the doors and to other structures, both man-made, such as
            bridges, or natural, such as courses of water, paying attention to the element of the spatial perspective,
            that emerges, now, in many cases of urban renewal and thanks to which is created an interaction between the
            city and the outside world.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/53</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>City Walls, City Gates, Town Planning, Perspective, Roman Cities</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.30</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>54</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">The Territory of Mesagne (Br) between the Roman Age and Late Antiquity</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Giovanna Cera</name>
                <email>giovanna.cera@unisalento.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università del Salento, Department of Cultural Heritage</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The results of the surveys made in the Brindisi area, territory of Mesagne, have
            produced new data demonstrating in the importance of systematic explorations to increase the knowledge of
            the forms of territorial organisation. Between the main historical phases that have characterised this area,
            we intend to present the one between the Roman Age and the Late Antiquity. A period that, unlike other
            districts (even neighbouring), reveals for the Brindisi area a clear increase of the rural population and
            deep changes in forms of land use.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/54</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Settlement Development, Roman Imperial Age, Rural Economy, Land Use, Road Network</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.31</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>55</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Indagini multidisciplinari ad Aquinum: la valorizzazione delle conoscenze</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Giuseppe Ceraudo</name>
                <email>giuseppe.ceraudo@unisalento.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università del Salento</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The urban area of Aquinum, a Roman city situated along via Latina between Frosinone
            (Frusino) and Cassino (Casinum), was investigated by aero-topographical studies, geophysical prospecting and
            archaeological field survey. All research activity was done by the Laboratory of Ancient Topography and
            Photogrammentry of the University of Salento. The executed explorative interventions have considered the
            results of the data processed as well as all documents related to the systematic surveys realised in the
            framework of the Ager Aquinas project. The substance of the archaeological deposits, the wealth of ancient
            materials and the remains highlighted constitute indicators of positive conditions for the planning of
            archaeological research oriented to confirming all that was individuated by the field surveys, aerial
            photographs and geophysical prospecting. These studies have allowed the reconstruction of the urban layout
            of Aquinum. Planning for the archaeological interventions was based not only on the results but also on the
            processing of data regarding field survey and on the compelling need for the preservation of the area.
            Starting with the collected data, six archaeological excavation campaigns have been carried out between 2009
            and 2014 in Aquinum. The research, after confirming the aerotopographical and geophysical results, focused
            on an area of the town that, until that time, had provided nothing useful for the recognition of monuments
            and urban spaces. Great results have been obtained thanks to the archaeological excavation campaigns led at
            the heart of the ancient Roman town. Knowledge of a central part of the built-up area has improved including
            where there are public buildings already known (theatre, an apsis-building) and unknown (public thermal
            baths). This is the keystone for better protection of the archaeological site and to future preservation for
            the area.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/55</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Aquinum, Aero-Topographical Studies, Geophysical Prospecting and Archaeological Field Survey,
                Public Thermal Baths
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.32</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>56</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">New Approaches in Landscape Analysis of the Bronze Age in Central-Western Sardinia: the
            Area of Mogoro (Oristano – Italy)
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Ricardo Cicilloni</name>
                <email>r.cicilloni@unica.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Giuseppina Ragucci</name>
                <email>gragucci@tiscali.it</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Marco Cabras</name>
                <email>marcocabras@correo.ugr.es</email>
                <affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Alberto Mossa</name>
                <email>mossaalberto1@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>3</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Department of History, Cultural Heritage and Territory, University of
                Cagliari (Italy)
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Ministry of Education, Universities and Research (Italy)
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="2">PhD Candidate, Doctorado en Historia y Artes – Arquelogía y Cultura
                Material, Universidad de Granada (Spain)
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="3">Postgraduate student, Postgraduate School in Archaeological Goods,
                University of Cagliari (Italy)
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Research on the prehistoric and proto-historic landscape in Sardinia (Italy) allows
            knowledge and analysis of the island’s archaeological heritage. Besides, recent studies have aimed to
            delineate the type of relationship that the prehistoric and proto-historic societies established with the
            variegated Sardinian landscape in connection with the ways of articulation and territorial appropriation,
            without neglecting the important and fundamental aspect of economic organisation of the territory. From this
            point of view, we want to analyse, as a sample-area, the region that includes the communal territory of
            Mogoro, in central-western Sardinia. Particularly we studied the ways of anthropisation and fruition of the
            landscape in proto-historic age, with the objective to reconstruct, through the study of the settlements and
            the relationships among them, some of the economic and social aspects of those groups of nuragic culture
            that enjoyed this area from the Middle Bronze Age to the Iron Age. The area of Mogoro has been intensively
            investigated from the half of the past century; the investigations then culminated with the stratigraphical
            investigation carried out beginning in 1994 near the site of Cuccurada, the main centre of an articulated
            territorial system including a rich network of monuments related to the nuragic civilisation, such as
            nuraghi, giants’ tombs and villages. In this work we present the results obtained through various research
            methods: geomorphological analysis, spatial analyst GIS tools (Viewshed, Cost Surface and Least-cost path
            analyses) and multivariate analysis (cluster and principal components analysis) that allow us to set a new
            hypothesis on population dynamics in this area and to individuate, among proto-historical monuments, one or
            more homogeneous and distinguished groups, starting from a database that results from indexing
            geomorphological characteristics.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/56</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Protohistory, Nuraghi, Landscape, GIS, Multivariate Analysis</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.33</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>57</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Divisioni agrarie antiche nel territorio di Taranto</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Fiorella De Luca</name>
                <email>f.deluca@ibam.cnr.it</email>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <abstract language="eng">L’analisi delle presenze archeologiche e della loro distribuzione diacronica nel
            territorio intorno alla città di Taranto ha avuto come ovvia conseguenza una riflessione sulla presenza di
            divisioni agrarie antiche e sulla possibile esistenza, nella stessa area, di diversi sistemi di
            lottizzazione. Imprescindibile l’analisi dei dati storici dando per scontato che uno o più interventi di
            parcellizzazione siano avvenuti con il processo di romanizzazione.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/57</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords/>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.34</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>58</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Neolithic Settlements of the Tavoliere di Puglia (Foggia, southern Italy). Topographic
            Analysis, Interpretation and Restitution of Archaeological Traces in Aerial Photographs
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Patrizia Gentile</name>
                <email>patrizia.gentile@unisalento.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Research Fellow in Ancient Topography</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper is focused on investigating the prehistoric settlements of the Tavoliere di
            Puglia (Foggia, South Italy) through the analysis of archaeological traces in historical and recent aerial
            photographs, both vertical (IGM images taken in 1954 and in 1955, IRTA, AM and RAF photographs, colour
            orthophotos) and oblique. As is well known, the plain of the Tavoliere was densely inhabited during the
            Neolithic Age and analysis of aerial photographs showed noteworthy examples of archaeological evidence
            related to topographical organisation of villages, delimited by one or more ditches containing more or less
            dense series of compounds. Such complexes are located, in most cases, near waterways that have sometimes
            dried up, in the areas interfluvial or on plateaus and shallow edge of scarp; in the western sector of the
            territory not many prehistoric settlements appear in aerial photographs and they are mainly located at
            slight elevations, neighbouring modern farms. The georeferencing and graphic rendering of archaeological
            traces of the Neolithic settlement allowed the measurement of their extension. In some cases the analysis of
            archeological traces in aerial photographs have found a topographic continuity between Neolithic settlements
            and Medieval fortifications, in areas characterised by the presence of slight hills featuring geological
            outcrop (locally known as “crusta”); this data has been confirmed by field survey. The interpretation of the
            many visible traces, their geo-referencing and graphic rendering, combined with topographical survey make an
            important contribution to the reconstruction of settlement dynamics of the prehistoric period. The
            integrated study of the historical and recent aerial photos was particularly functional when used to analyse
            archaeological contexts, no longer visible in recent aerial photos, and has facilitated a detailed analysis
            of the archaeological traces. The georeferenced data were, in part, controlled with field survey that has
            better defined the chronology of the archeological traces.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/58</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Neolithic Settlements, Archaeological Traces, Geo-Referencing and Graphic Rendering, Historical
                Aerial Photographs, Recent Aerial Photographs
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.35</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>59</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Studi geofisici per la topografia antica e l’archeologia del paesaggio: l’area
            archeologica di Flumeri (AV)
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Elisa Di Giovanni</name>
                <email>elidigio@libero.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Ida Gennarelli</name>
                <email>ida.gennarelli@beniculturali.it</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Paolo Mauriello</name>
                <email>paolo.mauriello@itabc.cnr.it</email>
                <affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Natascia Pizzano</name>
                <email>natasciapizzano@yahoo.it</email>
                <affiliationId>3</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Dipartimento di Scienze Umanistiche, Sociali e della Formazione,
                Università degli Studi del Molise; Gaia Business System s.r.l., Spin off dell’Università del Molise
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Soprintendenza Archeologia della Campania</affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="2">Istituto per le Tecnologie applicate ai Beni Culturali- CNR, Roma;
                Dipartimento di Scienze Umanistiche, Sociali e della Formazione, Università degli Studi del Molise
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="3">Dipartimento di Scienze Umanistiche, Sociali e della Formazione,
                Università degli Studi del Molise
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Historic landscape and cultural heritage are often integrated into a system of
            protection and valorisation through the global approach of archaeology and landscape archaeology. This
            system is conceived as a territorial study collecting all the evidence of human presence and its history,
            allowing the assessment of the historical and archaeological component through evolutionary dynamics.
            Therefore the study of landscape archaeology is central to the design and programming of territorial works.
            The “landscape system”, the result of the coexistence of environmental and human dynamics, has meant that
            territorial transformation processes have become the object of scientific interest assuming considerable
            political importance. In this paper, we present the preliminary results of a geophysical prospections for a
            map of the archaeological potential of the territory of Flumeri in Avellino, Italy. This diagnostic
            contribution was designed to give a distinctive and better representation of the territory. The scientific
            approach chosen for this project is the result of a multidisciplinary convergence: bibliographical and
            archival research, analysis of topographic and photogrammetric surveys, systematic investigations of the
            territory and geophysical survey. These diverse non-invasive geophysical methods allowed us to define and
            detail the archaeological potential of the studied area in a better way; by defining micro-areas of
            geophysical survey starting with defining macro-areas of high archaeological potential. This approach has a
            double value: the geophysical surveys serve as a support for the archaeological knowledge of the area and
            the archaeological knowledge helps towards the identification of areas for geophysical survey.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/59</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Fioccaglia, Irpinia, Geophysical Surveys, Ancient Topography, Landscape Archaeology</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.36</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>60</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Ancient Topography of the Mid Calore Valley: the City of Aeclanum and its Territory
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Immacolata Di Taranto</name>
                <email>immadit@libero.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Laboratory of Ancient Topography, Archaeology and Photogrammetry
                (LabTAF), University of Salento, Lecce, Italy
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The study area is located in the mid Calore valley, between the Calore and the Ufita
            Rivers. From prehistoric times, the territory has constituted an important crossroad among Campania, Apulia
            and Lucania, ensuring a connection between the Tyrrenian and Adriatic coast. The importance of the area grew
            with the construction of the via Appia, in the third century BC. Along its route, as documented by itinerary
            sources, in the early first century BC the municipium of Aeclanum (Passo di Mirabella – Mirabella Eclano,
            AV) was founded. A significant part of the research project regards this city: archaeological field surveys
            were carried out in the urban area and along the city walls, still partially preserved, with the aim to
            clarify its route. The new collected data were georeferenced in an aerophotogrammetric map, together with
            the data deriving from 1960s archaeological excavations and systematic study of archival documents of the
            Superintendence of Salerno, Avellino, Benevento and Caserta Province. The map was realised in the LabTAF of
            the University of Salento and constitutes the first large scale archaeological map of the ancient city.
            Systematic archaeological field walking was carried out on the territory corresponding partially to the ager
            Aeclanensis. It aimed at the reconstruction of the ancient topography of the territory surrounding the Roman
            site thanks to the large number of settlements documented. These settlements attest to the inhabitation of
            the area since the prehistoric and proto-historic times to the Medieval period. All collected data are
            georeferenced in the archaeological map that also allows diachronic analyses of the territory.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/60</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Ancient Topography</keyword>
            <keyword>Aerial Archaeology</keyword>
            <keyword>Archaeological Map</keyword>
            <keyword>Photogrammetry</keyword>
            <keyword>Field Survey.</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.37</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>61</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Agricultural Terraces in Classical and Hellenistic Greece</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Stavros Dimakopoulos</name>
                <email>dimakopoulos.stavros@windowslive.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Aristotle University of Thessaloniki</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Agricultural terraces have been a necessary element in the landscapes of Classical and
            Hellenistic periods in many areas of the Greek world. These terraces, formed by long terrace walls, shaped
            the slopes in the proximity of the farmhouses in order to facilitate exploitation of the land by the
            farmers, providing all the necessary conditions for efficient and effective cultivation of olive trees,
            grains, vines and almost any other crop. Various sites with agricultural terraces in the area of Attica,
            especially in the territory of the ancient deme of Atene (such as PH 2 in Aghia Photini and TH 18/42 in
            Thymari) as well as the Cycladic islands (Delos and Kea), dated to the Classical and Hellenistic period, are
            provided in this paper as some very characteristic examples of ancient terraced systems. Despite the
            thorough discussions about the dating of agricultural terraces in previous years, the issue of dating them
            back to ancient years remains an existent question for some scholars. Nevertheless, the sites mentioned here
            offer fairly good evidence for a dating in the fifth or fourth centuries BC. Furthermore, all these cases
            seem to share a common factor: their construction results from or is related to demographic criteria, such
            as the population growth of every area.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/61</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Terraces, Agriculture, Rural, Greece, Classical landscape</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.38</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>62</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Roman Rural Landscape of High Guadalquivir (Jaén) Lagoons</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Alejandro Fornell Muñoz</name>
                <email>afornell@ujaen.es</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Universidad de Jaén</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">A large number of lakes, lagoons, deltas, wetlands and flood plains converge in
            Andalusia. The analysis of lake and marsh areas during Roman times has been a historical subject
            insufficiently considered so far by Spanish historiographers. This research aims to undertake the study of
            those more significant cases of High Guadalquivir (Jaén), always within the Roman Baetica context. Focusing
            on the interaction among culture and environment, landscape ecology and socio-natural systems, the authors
            aim to comprehend the relation of rural settlements to these environments to study various methods of
            exploiting lagoon areas and to analyse lacustrine landscapes in the historical context of the Roman period.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/62</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Wetlands, Written Sources, Archaeology, Baetica, High Guadalquivir</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.39</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>63</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Ancient Topography Research in the Territory of Rodì-Milici (Messina): Preliminary
            Results
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Caterina Ingoglia</name>
                <email>caterina.ingoglia@unime.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Giuseppe Scardozzi</name>
                <email>g.scardozzi@ibam.cnr.it</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">University of Messina, Department of Ancient and Modern Cultures,
                Messina
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">National Research Council of Italy – Institute for Archaeological and
                Monumental Heritage, Lecce
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The paper concerns a research project carried out since 2011 by the Department of
            Sciences on the Antiquity of the University of Messina and the Institute for Archaeological and Monumental
            Heritage of the Italian National Research Council. The project is aimed at the reconstruction of the ancient
            topography of the territory of the modern village of Rodì-Milici, in the Province of Messina.
            The first campaign of systematic archaeological and topographical surveys, using a differential GPS system
            and a Laser Scanner, were performed in the hills to the west and south-west of the two villages, in
            particular on the large plateau between Monte Ciappa, to the north, and Pizzo Cocuzza, to the south. The
            investigated area was identified by L. Bernabò Brea, at the beginning of the 1950s, with the site of the
            ancient city of Longane. It had a strategic location for the control of the valleys of the Patrì and
            Mazzarrà rivers (respectively to the east and west of the investigated area) which constituted important
            routes of connection and traffic between the Tyrrhenian coast, the Monti Peloritani area and the Ionian
            coast of Sicily.
            The recent research, in integration with previous studies, acquired new data about the Archaic settlement
            that had an organisation strictly integrated to the topographical context and a structure different from
            traditional Greek colonies. The settlement on the plateau did not have a regular plan but seems organised
            into quite well distinguished inhabited, productive and sacred areas, while other areas are free of
            structures. It was protected by the two fortified hills (Monte Ciappa and Pizzo Cocuzza) which controlled
            the natural entrances to the plateau from north and south; the necropolises were located to the north-east
            and south of these hills, along the principal ways to arrive to the settlement.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/63</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Archaeological survey</keyword>
            <keyword>Longane</keyword>
            <keyword>Monte Ciappa</keyword>
            <keyword>Archaic period</keyword>
            <keyword>Patrì river valley</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.40</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>64</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Archeologia dei paesaggi: il territorio di Licata (AG) e la bassa valle dell’Himera
            meridionale
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Gioacchino Francesco La Torre</name>
                <email>gflatorre@unime.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Alessio Toscano Raffa</name>
                <email>a.toscanoraffa@hotmail.it</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università degli studi di Messina</affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">CNR-IBAM Catania</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The contribution presents a summary of the methodology and preliminary results of the
            research project Finziade and Lower Valley of Southern Himera of the Department of Ancient and Modern
            Civilisations, University of Messina. The goal of this project was to reconstruct how the territory of
            Licata (AG) on the southern coast of Sicily was settled. The area is of significant importance in the
            process of colonisation of the island since it is at the mouth of the main river. Monte Sant’Angelo, where
            the Hellenistic city of Finziade was found, was the subject of systematic investigations and monographic
            studies by the University of Messina. A recent analysis (2010-2012) of the so-called “Mountain”, the range
            of hills around Finziade, was the subject of a doctoral project (in press) that presented a detailed
            representation of the area’s settlement dynamic from prehistory to Late Antiquity. In 2012, on the basis of
            the new research, it was decided to expand the framework of the investigation by analysing the vast plains
            and the hills surrounding the “Mountain”. This research allows us to make the first historic assessment and
            settlement models, both relating to the period before the foundation of Finziade (282 BC) and for the later
            periods. The greatest population density is recorded in the “Castellucciana Age”, in the first half of the
            second millennium BC and later, after the foundation of Agrigento, with numerous nuclei of a non-urban
            nature, and in the early Hellenistic period with numerous rural and military settlements, among which emerge
            the two fortified towns of Monte Sole and Poggio Marcato d’Agnone. Important is the finding of several new
            areas containing clay fragments of the Imperial Era and Late Antiquity, probably due to rural villages or
            production centres. These villages, probably following a long tradition, exploited the fertile soil and used
            the port at the mouth of the Himera River, as remembered in the land and sea routes from the Late Roman
            period.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/64</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Landscape Archaeology, Rural Settlements, Survey, Sicily, Finziade</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.41</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>65</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">La trasformazione storico-topografica delle aree di confine: un esempio dal suburbio ovest
            di Roma
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Mirella Serlorenzi</name>
                <email>mirella.serlorenzi@beniculturali.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Giorgia Leoni</name>
                <email>giorgia.leoni@beniculturali.it</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Federica Lamonaca</name>
                <email>federica.lamonaca@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Soprintendenza Speciale per il Colosseo, il Museo Nazionale Romano e
                l’Area Archeologica di Roma
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Collaboratrice Progetto SITAR</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Rome’s contemporary city-structure in municipalities incorporated into the modern
            suburbs those boundary areas that in ancient times spread from the city walls (i.e. the urbanised city)
            towards the territory, forming a transit zone between city and country. The present paper intends to
            highlight the significance of these areas, main indicators not only from a historic-archaeological point of
            view, with respect to the knowledge of the ancient settlement’s distribution and evolution within the
            territory, but especially with regards to the modern landscape’s transformation, becoming pivotal areas that
            urbanists and town planners should take into consideration for conservation and usage.
            Our study analyses the territory of Rome’s Municipio XIII EST. This area shows a landscape that underwent a
            radical transformation throughout centuries, due to the changed requirements of the different social
            realities that followed each other from ancient Roman times until today. This casestudy shows clearly how
            the strong urbanistic expansion that started strongly in the 1960s extended like wild fire from the city
            centre towards the outside, becoming a rural landscape characterised by small properties and vast rural
            estates, on a surface with high housing industry. This caused the obliteration of the ancient landscape
            order, directly absorbed into the city and covered under many cement layers, without even verifying the
            historical value in previous forms of rural settlement. The widespread use of new technologies and
            territorial informative systems, like SITAR, Sistema Informativo Territoriale Archeologico di Roma of the
            Soprintendenza Speciale per il Colosseo, il Museo Nazionale Romano e l’Area Centrale di Roma, allows us to
            put together in a more rapid and complete way all the information from the various sources (historical
            cartographies, archives and bibliographic research, archaeological exploration of material data) and enables
            the knowledge and reconstruction of historical contexts.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/65</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Archaeology, Ancient Topography, Landscape Archaeology, Landscape Planning, Archaeological
                Protection
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.42</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>66</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Carta Archeologica D’italia – Forma Italiae Project: Research Method</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Maria Luisa Marchi</name>
                <email>marialuisa.marchi@unifg.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università di Foggia, Dipartimento di Studi Umanistici</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper presents the research method applied to the Archaeological Map of Italy –
            Forma Italiae project, comprising to date the Ager Venusinus project (completed) and the Ager Lucerinus
            project (ongoing). The methodology of the project is based on the extensive and systematic survey of the
            entire selected district. The countryside is systematically searched by groups of students and researchers
            in different seasons, time of the day, weather and visibility conditions, and status of cultivation of the
            ground. The GPS georeferenced data are integrated in a GIS specifically realised. The results of the
            research projects relating to the territory of the Luceria’s colony, in Apulia, starting from the area of
            the medieval site of Montecorvino, in the Daunian district is presented. So far the part of the vast
            territory of Lucera studied concerns the area North-East of the ancient Latin colony. Discussed here are
            studies conducted on the western area, towards the Daunian subappennine and in particular focused on the
            territory of the municipalities of Lucera, Pietramontecorvino, Motta Montecorvino, and Volturino. This area,
            in fact, is the object of research that includes the whole of the Fortore River valley. The data emerging
            from recent surveys show a large population over the time-span from prehistory to the High Middle Ages. The
            settlements of the Neolithic and Bronze ages, so far identified, are placed on vast plains; on the northern
            sector of the territory, it is possible to catch a glimpse of traces of a village characterised by the
            typical C shaped ditch, with huts located inside. A very interesting part of our project regards Dauni and
            Samnite settlements in the period preceding the arrival of the Romans and the Romanisation of the area. The
            most notable transformations in the ancient landscape were undoubtedly produced by the Roman intervention
            that gave birth to the new colony and the planning of the village centre, which consequently led to the
            reorganisation of a vast territory and the division of the rural area into a dense network of small
            properties assigned to the settlers.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/66</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Archaeological Map, Ancient Landscape, Limitatio and Centuriatio, Aerial Photography, GIS</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.43</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>67</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Archeologia Globale ad Egnazia: nuove acquisizioni dalla città e dal territorio</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Gianluca Mastrocinque</name>
                <email>gianluca.mastrocinque@uniba.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università degli Studi di Bari, Dipartimento di Studi Umanistici,
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The data presented are the preliminary results of the interdisciplinary project FIRB
            named Landscape archaeology of the Adriatic “Puglia” in the Roman Age: innovative technologies for
            sustainable planning and knowledge of cultural identity, carried out since 2013 by the University of Molise
            (with a leading role), the University of Bari and the Politecnico of Bari. The project deals with the old
            landscape of Egnazia through a global approach, underlining the role of settlement dynamics, exploitation of
            natural resources, manufacturing activities and trading and cultural exchanges within the Mediterranean
            basin. For the first time this topographic research has allowed a systematic review of the territory through
            a complete survey of the surface, mostly unknown before. The results of the survey are connected with the
            information about the old town, largely explored thanks to the Project Egnazia: from Digging to Evaluation
            directed by Raffaella Cassano since 2001. The analysis of the data, referring both to the town and the
            territory, allows the identification of a strong settling structure, which is subjected to many
            transformations from the Bronze Age till Late Antiquity. Only a single feature is always visible during the
            whole ancient history of this place: the settlement was deeply affected by the viability and the
            distribution of the “lame” (landform smaller than a ravine), deep furrows in the natural stony bedrock used
            as water tanks and a link road between the hills and the Adriatic Sea.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/67</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Landscape Archaeology, Egnazia, Systematic Survey, Cultural Heritage, Landscape</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.44</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>68</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Ploughsoil Assemblages and Beyond: Some Interpretative Challenges</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Simonetta Menchelli</name>
                <email>simonetta.menchelli@unipi.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università di Pisa, Dipartimento Civiltà e Forme del Sapere
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The present remarks derive from on-going topographic-archaeological projects focusing
            on North coastal Etruria and South Picenum. These studies apply a global archaeology approach that includes
            diachronic and interdisciplinary research. In our projects particular attention is being paid to
            palaeogeographic aspects. Processual methodology standards are applied to our research; nevertheless,
            geomorphologic, spatial and quantitative evidence is integrated with qualitative and symbolic data to
            reconstruct all the anthropic activities. Some remarks will be made about the informative potential of
            ploughsoil findings, landscape complexity, strategies in collecting and studying pottery and on the
            importance of considering the absence of particular categories of materials. Following this global approach
            and its consequential theoretical framework and rigorous methodology, archaeologists will be able to take up
            the interpretative challenge of defining landscapes in terms of their different components: sites, off-sites
            and their historical-functional classification. Obviously, the objective and subjective standards used for
            these classifications have to be explained clearly, so that the research results of a district can be used
            for comparisons and large-scale analyses.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/68</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Etruria, Picenum, Survey, Off-Sites, Pottery</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.45</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>69</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Archaeological Landscapes of Southern Apulia: Integration and Interpretation of Gis-Based
            Data in a Multi-Methodological Research
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Alfio Merico</name>
                <email>alfiomerico@libero.it</email>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Mariangela Sammarco</name>
                <email>mariangela.sammarco@libero.it</email>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <abstract language="eng">The Laboratory of Ancient Topography and Photogrammetry (LabTAF) at the University of
            Salento has long been engaged in the study of the ancient landscape, essentially through intensive field
            survey, the analysis of vertical and oblique multi-temporal aerial photographs and the development of a GIS
            system devoted to archaeological documentation. This integrated system of knowledge supports two main goals:
            sophisticated elaboration of complex datasets and practical possibilities for preservation of the
            archaeological heritage by providing efficient tools to the management of the territory and its cultural
            components. This contribution presents an analytic study of a sample area, chosen for its geomorphological
            characteristics and for its cultural complexity. This territory lies in the southern part of the Apulia
            Region, located between Lecce, the ancient Roman Lupiae, and its seaport at San Cataldo, along the Adriatic
            coast, covering about 85 km2 circa. Analysis of data from the field archaeological surveys, analysis of
            aerial photographs, archaeological aerial-survey and excavations revealed that the full functionality of the
            ancient harbour required the inland presence of a productive and receptive territory, with the distribution
            of rural settlements closely connected with the coast and the road system. The research presents an
            excellent opportunity for testing the potential of GIS systems in combination with conventional
            methodologies for landscape analysis, archaeological excavations and the application of new technologies.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/69</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Lecce, San Cataldo, GIS Data Management, Roman Harbour, Aerial Archaeology.</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.46</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>70</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Survey in the Inland Area of Lilybaeum</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Annapaola Mosca</name>
                <email>annapamo@tin.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Sapienza Università di Roma</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This survey focuses on the situation of the landscape and the ancient settlement of
            Lilybaeum in the countryside behind the modern centre of Mazara del Vallo. Based on the survey, the
            knowledge of the archaeological sites was applied to create an overview of the settlement dynamics in the
            territory. Evidence points to a widespread settlement, developed approximately from the end of the fourth
            century BC but established in the second century BC. It was linked mainly to the available water and
            environmental resources, especially agriculture, pastoralism, the quarries, the Mazaro River and to the easy
            possibility of trade, especially with North Africa. What stands out the most is the organisation of the
            settlements: it was possible to identify both large settlements and sometimes veritable villages, extending
            over several hectares, in this case similar to what has been found in other Sicilian districts, and to
            identify minor sites, probably functional to the villae or villages. The surface of a site in the San Miceli
            area, located near the banks of the Mazaro River, behind the port on the estuary of Mazara is exceptional.
            It has a very wide extension compared to other sites. Some of these sites, with remarkable signs of growth
            in the Late Imperial Age, especially in the fourth-fifth centuries AD, do not seem to survive beyond the
            sixth-seventh centuries AD. In a few cases we witness a continuum in the settlement, albeit in different
            forms compared to the previous periods, almost until the eleventh century AD in sites tied to the presence
            of wells, mills and, presumably, a road network. It was possible to redact an archaeological map from the
            archaeological data collected in the territory.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/70</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Sicily</keyword>
            <keyword>Lilybaeum</keyword>
            <keyword>Mazaro</keyword>
            <keyword>Mazara</keyword>
            <keyword>Survey.</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.47</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>71</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Verucchio and its Hinterland. Landscape Archaeology in the Valmarecchia</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Alessando Naso</name>
                <email>alessandro.naso@unina.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Simon Hye</name>
                <email>simon.hye@uibk.ac.at</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Christoph Baur</name>
                <email>christoph.baur@uibk.ac.at</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Formerly Universität Innsbruck, Institut für Archäologien, Innsbruck, now
                University Federico II, Dipartimento di Studi Umanistici, Naples
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Universität Innsbruck, Institut für Archäologien, Innsbruck
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The special position occupied in prehistoric research by the proto-urban centre of
            Verucchio in southern Romagna can be explained not only in the extraordinary finds that have been made in
            its necropolis but also in its position as an Etruscan bridgehead in Umbrian territory. However, the history
            of the origins of the settlement and its zone of influence are largely unexplored. The project Verucchio:
            City Development and Trade Links, Eleventh-Seventh Century BC, supported by the Austrian Science Fund (FWF),
            aims to address this desideratum at various levels such as survey, settlement patterns, trade routes and raw
            material supply. Research focuses on the areas directly adjacent to the valley of the river Marecchia, the
            main trade route between the Tyrrhenian Sea and the Adriatic coast in this area. Between 2009 and 2013 an
            archaeological landscape survey was successfully carried out and will be completed in 2015. Particular
            attention is being paid to topographically favoured hilltops and plateaus. In most of these locations
            archaeological remains with varying degrees of clarity can be identified through systematic site
            inspections. During the previous five survey campaigns more than 200 sites dating from the Stone Age to the
            Roman Imperial Age have been located. This preliminary paper aims to give an overview of the most important
            known and some of the newly discovered archaeological sites in the Marecchia Valley.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/71</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Bronze Age, Iron Age, Hilltop Settlements, Verucchio</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.48</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>72</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">L’intervisibilità. Analisi del paesaggio nella chora della colonia greca di Himera</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Maria Assunta Papa</name>
                <email>marypapa@virgilio.it </email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Laboratorio di Topografia Antica, Università di Palermo</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This study focuses on the analysis of the landscape in the territory of the colony of
            Himera. In particular, this work is inspired by a detailed examination conducted on the basis of parametric
            modelling, which has helped us to understand what factors (pedology, altimetry, geology, supply basins,
            etc.) had an effect in the settlement choices of the Imerese territory during the Colonial Age. We analysed
            the role intervisibility had between sites in the organisation of the landscape. By avoiding a deterministic
            logic, we intersected the data from previous surveys on the development of predictive models with the
            archaeological data, formulating hypotheses on the role that the main settlements in the area had on the
            control and economic management of the territory.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/72</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Chora, Settlement parameters, Landscape, intervisibility, GIS</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.49</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>73</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Distribution of Coastal Settlements of the Salento Peninsula. Topographic Analysis and
            Photo Interpretation of Historical and Recent Aerial Images
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Barbara Pezzulla</name>
                <email>barbara.pezzulla@unisalento.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Laboratory of Ancient Topography, Archaeology and Photogrammetry
                (LabTAF), Università del Salento, Lecce, Italy
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This study presents the results of topographic research on the Salento territory with a
            particular focus on the coast. The distribution of the coastal settlements, especially in prehistoric times,
            developed with a continuous chain of settlements, placed almost regularly along the Salento coast. The study
            of the aerophotographic documents has allowed the identification of large traces from residual moisture that
            would suggest the existence of some marsh basins, which would place certain settlements in one location,
            extremely isolated and protected, between sea and river. These conditions widely occur in both Salento
            coasts. In a few cases the same conditions can also be found in hinterland settlements where there are humid
            areas or seasonal wetlands. It seems clear that the archaeological sites of considerable size, milestone
            studies of traditional Italian prehistoric research (such as Scoglio del Tonno, Saturo, Torre Castelluccia,
            etc.), are characterised by the presence of a significant quantity of imported Aegean pottery and
            fortification works that often require great commitment and consistency. They alternate with minor
            settlements, sometimes equipped with fortifications as in the case of Bagnara, Torre Castiglione or Porto
            Badisco. A varied landscape also includes the large port facilities such as Brindisi, Taranto and Otranto,
            small landings, production sites and settlements of “purpurarii” (settlements dedicated to the extraction of
            purple pigment from gastropod molluscs). The preliminary results show complex situations, often not detected
            during the excavation work of the past, which may be better understood with systematic and extensive
            archaeological investigations, as is clear in the extraordinary evidence of the on going research in
            Rocavecchia.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/73</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Salento Peninsula, Coastal Archaeology, Air Photo Interpretation, Coastal Settlements, Ports and
                Harbours
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.50</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>74</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Landscape Archaeology in the Ager Telesinus: Scientific Results and Land-Use Planning
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Giuseppina Renda</name>
                <email>giuseppina.renda@unina2.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Seconda Università degli Studi di Napoli, Department of Humanities and
                Cultural Heritage
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper is focused on the territories of San Lorenzello, Guardia Sanframondi and
            Cerreto Sannita (district of Benevento, Campania), in the eastern area of the Ager Telesinus, along the
            route to the Apennines mountains through the Volturno, Titerno and Calore valleys. The research is related
            to the Project of the Archaeological Map of the Northern Campania, coordinated by S. Quilici Gigli. This
            territory has important archaeological risk, as archaeological records testify, including hill-forts with
            polygonal walls, the town of Telesia, the necropoleis and the ruins of the villae in the suburbium. The
            current expansion of the survey to both the eastern and western sectors offers a larger point of view to
            analyse wide-ranging topics such as the pre-Roman settlement and the interregional roads. New data are
            emerging on the prehistoric and protohistoric ages in the territory of Guardia Sanframondi, in the wide
            alluvial area closest to the Calore River. In the territory of San Lorenzello and Cerreto Sannita, new data
            was been collected by the author on a settlement of the pre-Roman times in the zones overlooking the Titerno
            valley. Studies and surveys in this area have had operating implications. Maps of archaeological risk, based
            on the archaeological map of the Ager Telesinus, were produced, thanks to collaboration between the
            University, Soprintendenza per i Beni Archeologici and the local Government, with the goal of creating a
            common strategy for land-use planning.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/74</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Ancient Topography, Campania, Landscape Archaeology, Land-use Planning, Archaeological Risk Map
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.51</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>75</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Sistemi di sfruttamento agricolo nell’ager Faliscus: I Prata di C. Egnatius (Corchiano –
            Vt)
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Francesca Rizzo</name>
                <email>francescarizzo83@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università degli Studi del Salento</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">In the Ager Faliscus, recent systematic surveys nearby the stream Fosso di Fustignano
            have revealed a complex system of landscape management in Antiquity, recorded by the inscription CIL XI
            7505, speaking about grazing lands (prata) in the Republican Age. The system has been described by A. Pasqui
            and partially positioned by S. Quilici Gigli. Recent explorations have allowed the location once again of
            the inscription nearby via Amerina and the discovery of a series of archaeological elements allowing the
            reconstruction of a complex system of organisation of the agricultural landscape strictly linked to the main
            viability. A well-turned structure of irrigation and drainage of the acreages proximal to the stream
            composed the work of C. Egnatius recorded in the epigraphy. Two different engineering solutions have been
            used, founded on the payload of the stream. Where the flow rate was minor, narrow rocky drains were realised
            to limit the range of the bed, to increase the level of the river and to permit the irrigation of the
            surrounding lands by a series of locks. The inscription of C. Egnatius is located just in front of one of
            these channels. Downstream, the irrigation system became more complex, using powerful dams.
            Outside one of these channels another inscription (Pr(ivatus?) Elix / Hic [-] VX [---]) may be concerned
            with the end of the water system and, at the same time, advises on the beginning of the area designated as
            private property. This interpretation corroborates the theory (already supported by aerophotointerpretation)
            of the presence of rural divisions in this area. The regular grid has an eight actus modulus and via Amerina
            constitutes the kardo. Then the work of C. Egnatius is simultaneous and inside the rural reorganisation of
            the Faliscan landscape in the aftermath of the Roman occupation.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/75</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Ager Faliscus, Corpus Agrimensorium Romanorum, Land Surveying, Rural Landscape, Water Management
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.52</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>76</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Exploring Valmarecchia. Diachrony of Population Development from the Roman Age to the Late
            Middle Ages in Central/Northern Italy: a Case Study of Emilia-Romagna (Southern Area) and Marche (Nothern
            Area)
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Daniele Sacco</name>
                <email>daniele.sacco@uniurb.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università degli studi di Urbino Carlo Bo, Department of Communication
                and Humanities (DISCUm)
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper summarises data gathered from an inter-regional research project conducted
            through land surveys, stratigraphic studies and the stratigraphic analysis of upstanding structures, within
            a program of the Department of Medieval Archaeology at the University of Urbino “Carlo Bo”. Surveys were
            carried out in the valley of the Marecchia River, Italy. The river flows through two regions, Emilia-Romagna
            and Marche, and two provinces, Rimini and Pesaro-Urbino. The project, which began in 2006, aims at
            presenting a diachronic landscape reconstruction by analysing landscapes transformation processes, from the
            Roman Age to the Renaissance. Special attention is devoted to the Middle Ages, the phenomenon of
            encastellation and to historical buildings. Within the project, extremely important, especially for the
            Middle Ages, are the surveys, carried out for the past 14 years at the archaeological site of the Castle of
            Monte Copiolo, hometown of the Counts of Montefeltro, who would later become Dukes of Urbino.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/76</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Landscape archaeology, Late antiquity, Encastellation, Valmarecchia, Rimini, Monte Copiolo
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.53</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>77</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Un progetto di ricerca tra topografia antica e archeologia dei paesaggi: l’Appia antica
            nel territorio di Beneventum
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Alfonso Santoriello</name>
                <email>asantori@unisa.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Amedeo Rossi</name>
                <email>arossi@unisa.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università degli Studi di Salerno, Dipartimento di Scienze del Patrimonio
                Culturale
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This work aims to present a research project on the landscapes of the ancient Appian
            Way in the area east of Benevento. The project, sponsored by the Soprintendenza Archeologica in
            collaboration with the University of Salerno, was born from the desire to deal, in an organic way, with the
            topographic reconstruction of the Appian roadway through a wider project of reconstruction of ancient
            landscapes.
            The Appian route, from Benevento, has been debated by various scholars who have provided several hypotheses.
            In particular, the road out of the city, headed east to Aeclanum. Its route to Ponte Rotto on the Calore
            River has not been identified yet and the studies carried out up to now are not certain of its topographical
            identification. What is known is that there had to be, just outside of the city, a statio, Nucriola or
            Nuceriola, located on the fourth mile, and the next ad Calorem, which probably was on the site of Ponte
            Rotto. The project Ancient Appia Landscapes wants to test the signs on the ground, the archaeological traces
            that these assumptions produced, trying to reconstruct not only the layout of the road, but also in a
            broader context, where the ancient settlement dynamics can be valued as a whole not as just an individual
            monument or road stretch.
            In this perspective, the research covers various methods and tools of investigation (the study of archives,
            historical maps, paleobotanical analysis, surface surveys, aerial photography interpretation,
            geomorphological surveys). Since 2010, a fieldwork characterised by systematic and thematic survey of
            particular sites started: while the surveys for particular sites allowed the retrieval of archaeological,
            monumental and accurate information in the area east of Benevento, the systematic surveys proposed the
            implementation of transects based on the geomorphological characteristics of the area. Since July 2011, a
            first campaign of thematic research concerning one of the assumptions of the reconstruction of the road
            network proposed in the early ’900 by Meomartini started. Intensive surveys provided the division of the
            territory in reconnaissance units measured on the morphology, on the surface visibility and on the division
            of land. From the first analysis of the context of findings accurate and aerial data emerged allowing to
            propose a topographical reconstruction of the route of the Consular way in a large and articulated
            settlement system.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/77</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Via Appia, Benevento, Paesaggio, Archaeological Survey, Geomorfologia</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>ita</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.54</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>78</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Carte archeologiche nella Provincia di Viterbo: tra conoscenza e conservazione</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Giuseppe Scardozzi</name>
                <email>g.scardozzi@ibam.cnr.it</email>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <abstract language="eng">The paper concerns three research projects promoted during the last 20 years by the
            University of Tuscia, aimed at the reconstruction of the ancient topography of areas inside southern
            Etruria, between Viterbo and the Tiber river valley; they are based on the systematic exploration of the
            territory and the production of archaeological maps. Two of these works, regarding the Ager Ciminius and
            Bomarzo-Bassano-Mugnano areas were completed and published in the series Carta Archeologica d’Italia -
            Contributi; the title of the series relates to the first project in the archaeological mapping of the
            national territory, performed in the last decades of the nineteenth century. The third research project,
            still in progress, regards the territory surrounding Viterbo, and between the city itself and the ancient
            settlement of Ferento and Acquarossa. The research projects produced archaeological maps aimed at supporting
            both the reconstruction of historical processes in a diachronic perspective and the activities in
            preservation of the archaeological heritage conducted by the Soprintendenza Archeologica per l’Etruria
            Meridionale. The systematic research activities allowed the collection of many new data about the ancient
            topography of these areas from the Proto-historic Age to the Medieval period, across the Etruscan and Roman
            epochs. The settlement pattern, the necropolises, the road networks, the rural and productive activities
            were studied and reconstructed. In general, the new data are very numerous in comparison to those previously
            known. Moreover, field-walking also provided the opportunity to document the condition of preservation of
            the archaeological evidence. In particular, in the area surrounding Viterbo, many ancient remains damaged or
            destroyed by new urbanisation and infrastructures are documented (also in comparison to the data documented
            during the surveys performed in the same territory at the beginning of 1970s). In the other two study areas,
            the most numerous damages are produced by mechanised agricultural works.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/78</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Archaeological Map, Southern Etruria, Agro Falisco, Knowledge, Conservation</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.55</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>79</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Ancient Topography in Southern Etruria: an Appraisal of Twenty Years of Research</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Marcello Spanu</name>
                <email>spanu@unitus.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università degli Studi della Tuscia, Viterbo</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">For over twenty years, the Università degli Studi della Tuscia has carried out and
            coordinated surveys in Southern Etruria, today’s province of Viterbo. These investigations are performed
            with traditional methods (collection of all kinds of data and their analysis, systematic field-walking and
            so on) combined with the employment of the latest technological applications. The area covered by these
            surveys is very wide (from the Tyrrhenian Sea to the Tiber River) and equally wide is the span of the
            connected studies, ranging from prehistoric to post-medieval periods. The deep geo-morphological diversities
            of this region have influenced, in the course of time, the occupation of the territory, its exploitation and
            settlement patterns. This research project has been partially motivated by the intention to fill a gap in
            our knowledge of a region which is very close to Rome and which has not been thoroughly examined until
            recently. The aim of this work is not only to redo a “census” of all the archaeological evidence of the
            territory but also to provide analysis according to coherent chronological phases or to specific topics
            (road-systems, distribution and typology of settlements, human activities and so on). A part of the data
            collected so far has been published in monographs by those responsible for the various surveys. In this
            paper, an overall presentation of the results will be outlined, with more general reflections on
            archaeological data and their potentiality in the field of the protection of cultural heritage (from
            preventive archaeology to the landscape planing).
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/79</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Southern Etruria, Ancient Topography, Archaeological Survey, Archaeological Mapping</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.56</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>80</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Topographical Reconstruction of Ancient Palermo: A Note on its Buildings for Public
            Spectacles and their Relation with the Roman-Period Civic Planning
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Paolo Storchi</name>
                <email>paolostorchi1@virgilio.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Sapienza Università di Roma</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Topographical studies in the last decades have greatly improved our knowledge of Roman
            Panormus (modern day Palermo) but many aspects of its urban planning still remain obscure. It is very hard
            work to clearly understand a city that has been continuously inhabited from at least the Iron Age to the
            present. This long standing existence implies countless transformations of its urban aspect. In particular
            the Arab domination, in the Middle Ages, erased even the memory of the ancient place names, so the
            toponomastic source that is often a fundamental tool for the ancient topographer is almost useless. Using
            the typical sources of ancient topography and landscape archaeology and its multidisciplinary approach can
            be exceedingly useful in understanding the ancient aspect of a living city. We found an important lack of
            information about ancient Palermo: the location of buildings designed for public spectacles. The epigraphic
            sources prove that in Palermo there was a theatre and an amphitheatre; from a Late-Antique source we can
            assume that there was also a circus. This paper’s aim is to suggest concrete hypotheses to identify the
            locations of all three of these buildings, discuss their position and their relation to the civic plan of
            Panormus. These results are important in understanding this city in a more complete way but also for the
            protection of its archaeological heritage: these three areas lie outside the ancient walls of Palermo and
            have hitherto been considered “low-risk areas” for archaeology. manifestations
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/80</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Ancient topography, Roman urbanism, Amphitheatre, Aerial photography, Ancient Sicily</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.57</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>81</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Upper Agri Valley (Basilicata) between Geomorphology and Ancient Settlements</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Francesco Tarlano</name>
                <email>francesco.tarlano@uniroma1.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Julian Bogdani</name>
                <email>julian.bogdani@unibo.it</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Antonio Priore</name>
                <email>geol.priore@tiscali.it</email>
                <affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Sapienza Università di Roma, PhD student</affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Alma Mater Studiorum - Università di Bologna</affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="2">Freelance professional geologist</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">In this paper we present the geoarchaeological and landscape project on the Upper Agri
            Valley (Basilicata). Between 2012 and 2015 we coordinated multidisciplinary research with the purpose of
            reconstructing the history and evolution of the territory, analysing the relationships between man and
            landscape from the Prehistory to the Middle Age. The studied area, an inland mountain valley situated in the
            ancient Lucania, is very important, because it is a fundamental route between the two coasts of Magna
            Graecia and because during the Roman period this valley was the territory in which Grumentum was born, one
            of the most important towns of Roman Southern Italy. Thanks to the dialogue between different competences,
            this project aims at understanding the settlements dynamics and the mutual influences between man and
            environment: indeed, we conducted geophysics and geoarchaeological investigations, archaeological surveys,
            cartographic and aerial photos studies, written sources analysis: in this way, different data are used to
            understand the landscape from a global point of view.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/81</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Agri, Grumentum, Topography, Lucania, Geoarchaeology</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.72</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>82</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Knowledge and CNR GIS for Cultural Heritage</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Patricia Tartara</name>
                <email>patrizia.tartara@cnr.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche - Ufficio Sistemi Informativi
                Territoriali per i Beni Culturali Piazzale Aldo Moro 7, 00185 Roma, tel. (06)49937425, mobile
                339-6109838
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">“Knowledge” of all kinds of evidence is important for scientists and researchers but it
            is also necessary for the protection and development of territory. It is, at the same time, the requisite
            basis for the right management of the territory and correct planning as it is also support for competent
            territorial administrations. This paper describes how the Italian National GIS for Cultural Heritage
            collects, records and presents archaeological and environmental data from several Regions for use in
            planning and other management regimes.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/82</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Ancient Topography, Survey, Aerial Monitoring, GIS Related to Data Base, Digital Cartography
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.73</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>83</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Aerial photographs and topographical territorial analysis: some case studies in the
            Vestine area (Abruzzo)
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Patricia Tartara</name>
                <email>patrizia.tartara@cnr.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche - Ufficio Sistemi Informativi
                Territoriali per i Beni Culturali Piazzale Aldo Moro 7, 00185 Roma, tel. (06)49937425, mobile
                339-6109838
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Data gathered by survey, photointerpretation of historical and recent aerial
            photographs, archives, bibliography, local bibliography and oral information, give an interesting picture of
            population settlement patterns in the Region of Abruzzo. Since prehistoric periods, the area along the Royal
            Sheep Track (Tratturo Regio) has been controlled by hilltop settlements as an ancient commercial route. The
            settlement pattern, on a local scale, still survives today.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/83</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Monitorig Flights, Photogrammetric Restitution, Field Survey, Aerial Photographs, Cartography
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.58</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>84</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Examining the Utility of Model Calibration and Verification as a Means of Testing
            Archaeological Computational Models
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Marieka Brouwer Burg</name>
                <email>Marieka.brouwer-burg@unh.edu</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">University of New Hampshire, Department of Anthropology, Durham, NH 03824
                USA
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The increasing sophistication and complexity of archaeological models has precluded
            easy testing of such models, and oftentimes requires assessments that can be as lengthy and complicated as
            the initial model design and execution. Here, a multi-criteria decision-based model developed to simulate
            hunter-gatherer land use decisions in the Post-Glacial Netherlands is discussed. To approximate when and
            where uncertainty occurs, a sensitivity analysis is implemented that involves varying input parameter
            weights to determine those parameters with the greatest potential impact on model output. This process
            incorporates linked combinations of statistical and qualitative tests that are unique to each stage of the
            modeling. While the sensitivity analysis described allows modellers to become better acquainted with both
            their models and data – and the inherent limitations that lie therein – the utility of such a heuristic
            exercise is debatable. Thus, another approach is proposed that involves running two spatial analyses that
            target the same question of human land use decision-making from different directions and harnessing
            different data. This procedure has the ability to provide archaeological modellers with a better
            approximation of the robustness of each spatial analysis, especially when the two analyses converge upon
            similar answers. When the spatial analyses do not produce similarly patterned results, we know it is time to
            go “back to the drawing board” and reassess the meta-issue of whether the questions we are asking can be
            answered via our modeling abstractions. These issues are of no small import because if archaeological models
            are to resonate with researchers conducting similar simulative and decision-based models in other fields,
            then we must implement comparable post-process tests on our models too.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/84</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Multi-Criteria Decision Model</keyword>
            <keyword>Sensitivity Analysis</keyword>
            <keyword>Least Cost Path And Current Analysis</keyword>
            <keyword>Mesolithic Hunter-Gatherers</keyword>
            <keyword>The Netherlands</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.59</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>85</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Simulating the Farm: Computational Modelling of Cattle and Sheep Herd Dynamics for the
            Analysis of Past Animal Husbandry Practices
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Jamie Joyce</name>
                <email>j.a.joyce@vu.nl</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Philip Verhagen</name>
                <email>j.w.h.p.verhagen@vu.nl</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Faculty of Humanities, The Netherlands
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This study forms part of a larger project analysing the development of the cultural
            landscape in the Dutch Roman limes region, including the development of the rural economy. The primary
            research aim in this study is to investigate changes in pastoral production as a result of differing
            population dynamics of sheep and cattle herds subjected to different animal husbandry practices. Differences
            between such practices have not been considered in previous models of pastoral production in the region
            where herds have been treated as static entities. In this study we simulated different animal husbandry
            strategies based on trends and developments inferred from the faunal record in a well-documented area of the
            limes zone. The results of these simulations were analysed for differences in population viability, as well
            as relative differences in production of meat, wool and manure, and relative requirements for pastureland
            requirements and labour. Our analysis shows that cattle and sheep herds exploited for products supplied by
            the animals whilst living (manure and traction from cattle, wool from sheep) exhibit higher growth rates
            than herds exploited for meat. In addition, they are able to supply larger quantities of calories. However
            these herds have higher requirements for labour and land, presenting a possibly limiting factor. We conclude
            that, in addition to complementing intensification and extensification of arable farming observed in the
            region, agriculturalists would have benefitted from herds with higher growth rates, particularly given their
            risk-aversion behavior during periods of economic uncertainty. These simulations will be subsequently used
            to produce more nuanced scenarios of pastoral production within agent-based modelling of the mixed rural
            economy in the Dutch Roman limes zone.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/85</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Dutch Roman limes, System Dynamics, Zooarchaeology, Roman Agriculture</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.60</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>86</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Estimating “Land Use Heritage” to Model Changes in Archaeological Settlement Patterns
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Laure Nuninger</name>
                <email>laure.nuninger@univ-fcomte.fr</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Philip Verhagen</name>
                <email>j.w.h.p.verhagen@vu.nl</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Frédérique Bertoncello</name>
                <email>frederique.bertoncello@cepam.cnrs.fr</email>
                <affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Angelo Castrorao Barba</name>
                <email>a.castrorao@virgilio.it</email>
                <affiliationId>3</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Chrono-Environnement (UMR 6249, CNRS/UFC), MSHE C. N. Ledoux (USR 3124,
                CNRS/ UFC), Besançon, France
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Faculty of Humanities, The Netherlands
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="2">CEPAM (UMR 7264, CNRS), Nice, France</affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="3">University of Palermo, Interdepartmental Centre for Research on
                Technology-Environment Interaction (CIRITA), Italy
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper describes a method to calculate a “land use heritage map” based on the
            concept of “memory of landscape”. Such a map can be seen as one variable among many others that can
            influence site location preference and can be used as input for archaeological predictive models. The
            computed values equate to an index of long-term land use intensity. This index aims to assess the influence
            of previous occupation of the landscape on settlement location, in particular Roman rural settlements. The
            method was applied on a micro-region located in Southern France in order to test its workability. It is
            concluded that the method is potentially suitable for incorporating the influence of previous occupation in
            predictive modelling but still needs further refinement in order to be more generally applicable.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/86</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Predictive Modelling, Path Dependency, Land Use, Roman Rural Settlement, Kernel Density Estimates
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.61</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>87</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Predictive Modelling of Younger Dryas Archaeological Remains in Southern Flevoland
            (Central Netherlands)
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>D.F.A.M. van den Biggelaar</name>
                <email>don.vanden.biggelaar@vu.nl</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>S.J. Kluiving</name>
                <email>s.j.kluiving@vu.nl</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>J. Kolen</name>
                <email>j.c.a.kolen@arch.leidenuniv.nl</email>
                <affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>C. Kasse</name>
                <email>c.kasse@vu.nl</email>
                <affiliationId>3</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Institute for Geo- and Bioarchaeology,
                Faculty of Earth and Life Sciences, De Boelelaan 1085, 1081 HV Amsterdam, The Netherlands.
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Institute for Geo- and Bioarchaeology,
                Faculty of Earth and Life Sciences; Department of Archaeology, Ancient History of Mediterranean Studies
                and Near Eastern Studies, Faculty of Arts; Research Institute for the heritage and history of the
                Cultural Landscape and Urban; Environment (CLUE), Faculty of Arts, De Boelelaan 1105, 1081 HV Amsterdam,
                The Netherlands.
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="2">Universiteit Leiden, Faculty of Archaeology; Centre for Global Heritage
                and Development, Einsteinweg 2, 2333 CC Leiden, The Netherlands.
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="3">Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Cluster Earth and Climate, Faculty of Earth
                and Life Sciences, De Boelelaan 1085, 1081 HV Amsterdam, The Netherlands.
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">In this research locations are selected in Southern Flevoland (Central Netherlands)
            which are most likely to contain archaeological remains dating to the Younger Dryas (YD) (12,900-11,700 cal
            BP). To map and determine these locations two steps are performed:
            1) The Pleistocene surface of Southern Flevoland is classified into landforms using a GIS application based
            on Topographic Position Index.
            2) Data on the geomorphological setting and the distance to the nearest freshwater source of well-dated YD
            archaeological sites in the Northwest European Plain are extrapolated to the study area.
            The inductive predictive model indicates that elevated areas in close proximity to a freshwater source have
            the highest probability to contain YD archaeological remains. For potential Federmesser remains a maximum
            distance of 1500 m from the Eem fluvial system is estimated and for potential Ahrensburgian remains a
            maximum distance of 2500 metres. The areas with potential YD archaeological remains constitute less than 10%
            of the total study area. The detailed and well-preserved Pleistocene surface in the study area, combined
            with potentially well-preserved YD remains due to the Holocene sediment cover, is of major importance for
            future studies on landscape exploitation by prehistoric hunter – fisher – gatherers. Reconstructing
            landscape exploitation opens up new avenues to study subsistence economy, settlement patterns and spatial
            organisation of past societies.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/87</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Hunter – Fisher – Gatherer Landscape Exploitation, Pleistocene Surface Mapping, Predictive
                Modelling, Southern Flevoland, Younger Dryas
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.62</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>88</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Modelling the Dynamics of Demography in the Dutch Roman Limes Zone</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Philip Verhagen</name>
                <email>j.w.h.p.verhagen@vu.nl</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Jamie Joyce</name>
                <email>j.a.joyce@vu.nl</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Mark Groenhuizen</name>
                <email>m.r.groenhuijzen@vu.nl</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Faculty of Humanities, The Netherlands
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">In this paper we present the first results of a study that aims to better understand
            and model the size and development of population in the Dutch Roman limes zone, as part of a larger research
            project investigating the development of the cultural landscape in the area. Earlier estimates of population
            size have only used general assumptions based on settlement density and supposed Roman army recruitment
            requirements and have not considered in any detail the factors influencing population growth and decline.
            This paper first presents the existing evidence for estimating population size in the area and then
            discusses the evidence for mortality and fertility estimates in the Roman period, necessary to better
            understand the large-scale demographic processes involved. From this evidence, new estimates for population
            size in the Early and Middle Roman period are calculated, using agent-based modelling to better understand
            the dynamics of population growth and the effects of recruitment of soldiers by the Roman army. It is
            concluded that earlier calculations underestimated the potential for population growth as well as the effect
            of forced recruitment on demography.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/88</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Roman limes, Dutch River Area, Batavians, Demography, Agent-Based Modelling</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.63</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>89</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Human Energetics and the Modelling of Cultural Landscapes</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Thomas G. Whitley</name>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">University of Western Australia, Asst. Professor of Archaeology, M257,
                Perth, WA, 6009, Australia
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Landscape archaeology is a broad field that seeks to place what we consider
            “archaeological” into a spatial context, whether that be literal, theoretical, or conceptual. With more
            recent approaches to social-spatial simulation (through GIS or agent-based modelling techniques) this has
            entailed complex mathematical methods or procedures which can be quite difficult to evaluate or even
            understand as a representation of past human activity. It could be said that archaeological remains often
            drive the construction of the simulation, or conversely that social complexity is expected to organically
            emerge from simple programmed “rules” of behaviour in a frictionless or highly generalised manifold.
            Naturally, the result has been models that have been dismissed as missing the point, or being too simplistic
            to be of any use because they neither consider past people’s cognitive intentions nor the material remains
            that have been eradicated by taphonomic processes. Perhaps we need to redefine what it is that interests us
            as archaeologists. Is it finding sites, features and artefacts? Or is it understanding past human behaviour
            in the context of objective-oriented mechanisms, preferably within a spatial framework? If it is the latter,
            then maybe we need to look at modelling human energetics as both a past “spatial currency” and as a primary
            unit of analysis. Sites, artefacts and features are by-products in the human expression of energy across the
            landscape, and they should be defined and used as such in understanding and evaluating complex spatial
            models. A large-scale GIS simulation of the first century BC Helvetian subsistence economy (an on-going
            project) is used to illustrate these ideas.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/89</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>GIS, Simulation, Economic Modelling</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.64</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>90</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Introduction: Seeing Heritage through the Lens of Landscape – New Approaches in Landscape
            Archaeology Based on the Fusion of Heritage and Landscape
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Graham Fairclough</name>
                <email>graham.fairclough@newcastle.ac.uk</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Bas Pedroli</name>
                <email>bas.pedroli@wur.nl</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Niels Dabaut</name>
                <email>niels.dabaut@ugent.be</email>
                <affiliationId>2</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">McCord Centre for Landscape, University of Newcastle (UK), CHeriScape
                (www.cheriscape.eu),
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Wageningen University (NL), CHeriScape (www.cheriscape.eu),
            </affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="2">University of Newcastle (UK), CHeriScape (www.cheriscape.eu),
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper explains the genesis of the Seeing heritage through the lenses of landscape
            session organised at the LAC 2014 conference by the CHeriScape network. It introduces seven papers presented
            at the conferences (and summarises three others), contextualising them in the symbiotic relationship between
            landscape and heritage within modern European society, and draws from them, under the general themes used in
            the CHeriScape network, a series of common threads and conclusions that contribute to CHeriScape’s agenda.
            The discourse is located within the frame of three recent European policy documents, the European Landscape
            Convention, the Faro Convention on the Value of Cultural Heritage for Society and the ESF/COST Science
            Policy Briefing on landscape. The conclusions form part of the process of increasing the social relevance of
            landscape archaeology and its potential contribution to the grand challenges commonly identified in current
            policy-making debates.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/90</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>CHeriScape, Landscape and Heritage, European Landscape Convention, Faro Convention, Landscape SPB
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.65</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>91</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Archaeological and Ethnographic Survey in the Paikuli Area (Iraqi Kurdistan)</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Julian Bogdani</name>
                <email>julian.bogdani@unibo.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Luca Colliva</name>
                <email>luca.colliva@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Camilla Insom</name>
                <email>camillainsom@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>1</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università di Bologna</affiliationName>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="1">Sapienza Università di Roma</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The Italian Archaeological Mission in Iraqi Kurdistan (MAIKI) of the Sapienza
            University of Rome aims to study the archaeological, historical, linguistic and cultural development of the
            Kurdish region through a wide historical period. MAIKI started by focusing on the archaeological and
            philological analysis of the Sasanian site of Paikuli. In recent years, however, investigation has been
            expanded to include an accurate survey of the area between the Dyala and Basara rivers, around the main road
            that connects the city of Chamchamal to Darbandikhan, in order to implement a complete and updated
            archaeological map of the entire territory. The continuing work includes a preparatory study of the few
            bibliographical records available and an overall analysis of the accessible, current and historical
            satellite imagery in order to obtain a reliable context for the results of archaeological field surveys.
            During the field campaigns, which are currently suspended because of the political instability and war in
            the region, archaeological material was collected in all the visited sites and a detailed morphological and
            archaeometric study was set up. A complete map of the currently inhabited villages of the area has been
            compiled because up-to-date base cartography of the area did not exist; this new map has proved to be useful
            not only for locating archaeological records but also for the activities of the ethnological research that
            joined the Mission in 2013. The area suffered very much during Saddam Hussein’s Al-Anfal campaign when all
            of the people were forced to leave. The ethnological study will help to reveal the impact that these recent
            traumatic events have had on the preservation of the cultural heritage whilst supplying rich documentation
            for further investigation, including on relationship between man and territory, local economy, migration
            policies and religious practices.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/91</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Kurdistan, Landscape Archaeology, Near Eastern Archaeology, Archaeological Survey</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.66</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>92</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Connecting the Museum with the Landscape: a Geographical Solution for the Pigorini Museum,
            Rome
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Arjuna Cecchetti</name>
                <email>arjunacecchetti@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Independent Researcher – in collaboration with the Museo Nazionale
                Preistorico Etnografico “Luigi Pigorini”, Rome
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The Prehistoric Ethnographic National Museum “Luigi Pigorini” holds one of Europe’s
            most important collections of prehistoric archaeological material with contexts excavated beginning at the
            end of the nineteenth century. This paper illustrates the first steps towards a digitised model of the
            archives and of the Museum collection with the aim of refreshing the Museum’s memory by restoring lost
            connections between the landscape context and the historical documents of archaeological research (including
            old photographs, registers, notes and sketches). The methodological approach begins with the experience of
            the project SITAR, the web-based GIS of the Superintendence for the Archaeological Heritage of Rome. It
            intends to develop geographically-focused solutions to share the knowledge of the Museum with local
            communities and to highlight the connections between prehistoric finds and the current landscape, thus
            contributing to the formation of the community’s identity. This process intends to move the Museum towards a
            dynamic dimension and make it more accessible and meaningful for contemporary users.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/92</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Museum, Archives, Landscape, Public Archaeology, Crowd-Sourcing</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.67</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>93</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">The Landscape of Ancient Caere through Historic Air Photographs</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Patrizia Tartara</name>
                <email>patrizia.tartara@cnr.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche, Rome</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper briefly shows the use of an analysis of a large number of IGM 1930 glass
            slide negatives and an accurate photo-interpretation of cropmarks to create a particular view of the
            territory of ancient Caere, almost 30 km NW of Rome. This territory was covered by a great number of tumuli
            and tombs of different kind, giving a very strong and impressive sensation of power and wealth.
            Topographical analysis of the case study area by direct survey, field-checking and revision of previous data
            and pertinent documentation (bibliographic, public and private archives and information in loco, etc.) was
            accompanied by examination and analysis of historical and recent aerial photographs from different archives,
            with additional monitoring flights over areas of risk. The aim was to obtain an historical perspective of
            the territory to help the protection of cultural heritage remains, meet the need for the establishment of a
            global Cultural Heritage cadastre connected to studies for legal protection and enjoyment of great interest
            sites, and finally, not least, for a correct territorial planning.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/93</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Monitoring Flights, Photogrammetric Restitution, Field Survey, Aerial Photographs, Cartography.
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.68</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>94</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Appalachian Landscape and Architecture through the Lens of Extraction</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Peter Butler</name>
                <email>pebutler@mail.wvu.edu</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Charlie Yuill</name>
                <email>cyuill@wvu.edu</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">West Virginia University, Landscape Architecture Program, School of
                Design &amp; Community Development
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">Long considered by many historians as an “internal colony” (Haynes, 1997), the cultural
            landscape of the coalfields of McDowell County, southern West Virginia (USA) displays a palimpsest of
            political, social, cultural and environmental history. Drawing out some of the most valuable coal in the
            world, Pocahontas “smokeless” (McGehee, 2012), the grip of absentee landholders (Myers, 2008) on the region
            is reflected in legible traces on the land. Investigating remnant industrial terrain, modelled using LiDAR,
            brings patterns to the surface for interpretation and typological analysis (Opitz, 2012). From early mining
            forms, wildcat and prospect mines, to tunnel and later Mountain Top Removal (MTR), the morphology of the
            landscape evolved in line with machine technology and reflects the history of place. Communities constructed
            as work camps reveal an ordered geometry of control, a mnemonic of “corporate paternalism” (Garay, 2011);
            while the buildings of Gary, West Virginia, a US Coal and Coke Company model town evoke a Utopian efficiency
            and economy. Post-1950s boom time McDowell County counted 100,000 residents with cluttered Main Streets and
            overflowing rail lines. Today the population has dwindled to near 20,000 and the memory of early twentieth
            century industry in the “Free State of McDowell” is fast being erased either through neglect, abandonment or
            conscious elimination. MTR mining and the practice of filling valleys with waste rock obliterates topography
            at an unprecedented scale. Abandoned camps are washed away from the floodplain or intentionally removed.
            Smaller scale mining operations are swept away as new technologies raise the economic viability of thin coal
            seams. As the landscapes, communities, and buildings of McDowell County are reorganised and reshaped, a
            methodology for analysis through remote sensing and ground-truthing (Doenus et al, 2008; Gallagher &amp;
            Josephs, 2008; Horne, 2009) informs interpretive strategies in capturing narratives of place.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/94</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Cultural Landscape, Industrial Landscape, LiDAR, Interpretation</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.69</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>95</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">3D Laser Recording and the “Naturalised” Urban Landscape of Göreme, Kapadokya, Turkey
        </title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Carmela Crescenzi</name>
                <email>carmela.crescenzi@unifi.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Marcello Scalzo</name>
                <email>marcello.scalzo@unifi.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Giorgio Verdiani</name>
                <email>giorgio.verdiani@unifi.it</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Università degli studi di Firenze, Dipartimento di Architettura (DIDA)
            </affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">This paper presents research on the historic urban settlement and natural landscape
            between the Göreme and Kiliclar (Swords) valleys, located in Kapadokya, one of the most distinctive human
            and natural landscapes in the world, inscribed on the UNESCO World Heritage List in 1985. The research was
            part of the Italian Scientific Research Programs of Relevant National Interest (PRIN) programme Rupestrian
            Art and Habitats in Kapadokya (Turkey) and in Central and Southern Italy – Rock, Excavated Architecture,
            Painting: Between Knowledge, Preservation and Enhancement. The study area has all the features of rupestrian
            Mediterranean culture, encompassing a heritage developed over time with environmental, architectural and
            artistic elements. It tells a special story about ancient life, completing and widening our comprehension of
            the past. There are buildings of great architectural and pictorial qualities, such as the Tokali Kilise,
            Saint Eustachius and Saint Daniel, where it is still possible to read the old defensive system and the local
            way of life. Yet these cave settlements are at risk from deterioration. The research is centred on survey,
            especially on a digital survey carried out using 3D laser scanners for the architecture as well as of the
            natural stone structure of the settlement. In this way the first complete and detailed documentation of this
            area has been created, allowing the first studies on the urban character of this archaeological site. The
            research presented here will show a fully digital approach using 3D digital models aimed to investigate,
            read, preserve the information and disseminate the artistic and cultural values otherwise not easily
            accessible and continuously at risk of loss because of decay processes.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/95</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Rupestrian</keyword>
            <keyword>Turkey</keyword>
            <keyword>Kapadokya</keyword>
            <keyword>3D Laser Scanner</keyword>
            <keyword>Digital Survey</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.70</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>96</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Soundscape, Landscape and Cultural Heritage: A Case Study in Proto-Historic Italy</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Sonia Modica</name>
                <email>modica.sonia@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Sapienza Università di Roma</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">The dominant perceptual sense in western culture is certainly that of sight: the
            “vision” of the world, even in everyday language, tends to coincide with what is perceived as reality. Not
            surprisingly, our being in the world is increasingly defined from the perspective of a single “point of
            view”. The first consequence is the progressive absorption of the multisensory component, which inevitably
            characterises every act of perception, within the arrangements of an ever more debased and impoverished
            image. Landscape is an interface consisting of objects, situations and configurations that indicate precise
            locations of resources and meanings. Spatial configurations that allow the identification of a resource or a
            meaning can be both structural (such as a row of trees) and a type of energy (such as acoustic
            configurations or soundscape, or the light intensity, e.g. light spots within of a forest, or olfactory,
            e.g. smelling traces left by an animal). In this paper a case study is provided of some material contexts,
            examined through the conceptual lens of “soundscape” applied to archaeology. The examination of the sound
            components relates to pre-Roman Italy and involves the definition of “soundscape” as a subject of
            archaeological research. Soundscape frequently denotes the natural sound environment through its primary
            physical components such as the sounds of nature (wind, water, forests, birds, insects, animals), but it is
            also produced by human activity, and the outcomes of phonic instrumental artefacts and mechanical actions.
            The len is moved, therefore, from what is observed to what is heard; as regards archaeological analysis,
            data is projected onto culturally-contextualised acoustic scenery.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/96</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Soundscape, Latium, Rattles, Ornaments, Perception.</keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
    <record>
        <language>eng</language>
        <publisher>CLUE+ Research Institute for Culture, Cognition, History and Heritage</publisher>
        <journalTitle>LAC 2014 proceedings</journalTitle>
        <publicationDate>2016-10-31</publicationDate>
        <volume>0</volume>
        <issue>0</issue>
        <doi>10.5463/lac.2014.71</doi>
        <publisherRecordId>97</publisherRecordId>
        <title language="eng">Citizen Participation and Heritage Management in Rural Landscape Contexts</title>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <name>Jose M. Señorán Martín</name>
                <email>jose.m.senoran@gmail.com</email>
                <affiliationId>0</affiliationId>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <affiliationsList>
            <affiliationName affiliationId="0">Independent researcher</affiliationName>
        </affiliationsList>
        <abstract language="eng">‘The personal is political’ is one of Kate Millet’s most famous phrases. It refers to
            the mismatches between the needs of the citizenry and practices carried out by those in the political
            sphere. In our case, we can relate this to integrated heritage management, and more specifically, the
            policies implemented in recent years in rural contexts in Spain. This paper examines the case of the large
            number of Heritage Interpretation Centres, restoration of traditional structures, and archaeological
            excavations which were initiated from the 1990s by rural municipalities, with funding from the European
            Union (Leader Funds, mainly), but many of which a decade later have failed and been abandoned by public
            institutions. This paper argues that this was partly due to the lack of public participation in the
            development of these projects, which were managed vertically and asymmetrically, with the inhabitants of the
            towns excluded and unable to contribute their own vision. Future heritage management projects should be
            based on citizen participation and empowerment of the different local agents that are closer to heritage
            sites. Through a case study in northern Cáceres, a revitalisation of the rural northern Extremadura area is
            proposed based on sustainable heritage tourism and revolving around three key concepts: cultural landscape,
            heritage and empowerment. For this to be implemented successfully, we must deal with various characteristics
            which form the identity of the region, as well as the particular political development within northern
            Extremadura.
        </abstract>
        <fullTextUrl format="html">http://lac2014proceedings.nl/article/view/97</fullTextUrl>
        <keywords>
            <keyword>Landscape, Citizen Empowerment, Sustainable Tourism, Community Archaeology, Archaeological
                Heritage.
            </keyword>
        </keywords>
    </record>
</records>
